Hello and welcome back. My name is Brian Hartman
and I am an associate professor at Brigham
Young University.
In the frequentist interpretation, one treats
the vector of parameters theta as fixed yet
unknown, whereas the outcomes X are realizations
of random variables. With Bayesian statistical
models, one views both the model parameters
and the data as random variables. Once the
parameters have a distribution, we can use
probability tools to reflect and analyze this
uncertainty about the parameters theta. For
notation, we will think about theta as a random
vector and let pi of theta denote the distribution
of possible outcomes.
There are several advantages of the Bayesian
approach. One can describe the entire distribution
of parameters conditional on the data. This
allows one, for example, to provide probability
statements regarding the likelihood of parameters.
This approach allows analysts to blend information
known from other sources with the data in
a coherent manner. This topic is developed
in detail in the credibility chapter. The
Bayesian approach provides for a unified approach
for estimating parameters. Some non-Bayesian
methods, such as least squares, require an
approach to estimating variance components.
In contrast, in Bayesian methods, all parameters
can be treated in a similar fashion. It is
also convenient for explaining results to
consumers of the data analysis.
There are two main parts to the Bayesian model.
The prior distribution is your belief about
the parameters before any data is collected.
This is a great place to systematically include
expert opinion about the parameters or the
results from previous studies. The model distribution,
or the likelihood, is the contribution of
the data.
The prior and likelihood are combined using
Bayes’ rule to get the posterior distribution.
This is one of the main benefits of the Bayesian
paradigm, you have a belief, gather some data,
update that belief, gather more data. You
can continue that iterative process as long
as you would like. There is a saying that
today’s posterior is tomorrow’s prior.
Once you have the posterior distribution of
the parameters of interest, you can summarize
those parameters using a credible interval.
It sounds just like a confidence interval,
but is so much better because rather than
having to say “we are 95% confident that
the true parameter falls between a and b”
you can say what you really want to say “there
is a 0.95 probability that the parameter is
between a and b.”
How do we calculate the posterior distribution?
As mentioned on the previous slide, the posterior
distribution is equal to the likelihood times
the prior over the marginal. Notice that the
denominator does not depend on theta, the
parameter of interest. Therefore, the posterior
distribution is proportional to the likelihood
times the prior. That quantity is sometimes
called the kernel. If the kernel is proportional
to a known distribution, then we know the
exact posterior distribution. In most realistic
cases, we won’t know the closed-form of
the posterior distribution and will need to
simulate it using Markov chain Monte Carlo,
or MCMC. Additionally, sometimes we can use
normal approximations to make the MCMC more
efficient.
One conjugate family which allows us to find
the closed-form of the posterior is the Poisson-Gamma
family. If your data is Poisson Lambda distributed,
and you assume that lambda has a gamma alpha
theta prior, then the posterior distribution
of lambda is also gamma distributed with alpha
equal to the alpha from the prior plus the
sum of the x’s and theta equal to 1 over
the sample size plus one over the theta from
the prior.