Hello and welcome back. My name is Brian Hartman
and I am an associate professor at Brigham
Young University.
An outcome is potentially truncated when the
availability of an observation depends on
the outcome. In insurance, it is common for
observations to be truncated from the left
(or below) at d when the amount observed is
Y which is equal to x minus d only when x
is greater than or equal to d. In this case,
d may represent the deductible associated
with an insurance coverage. If the insured
loss is less than the deductible, then the
insurer does not observe the loss. If the
loss exceeds the deductible, then the excess
X minus d is the claim that the insurer covers.
Observations may also be truncated from the
right (or above) at d when the amount observed
is x only when x is less than d. Classic examples
of truncation from the right include X as
a measure of distance of a star. When the
distance exceeds a certain level d, the star
is no longer observable.
This slide can look intimidating, I am sorry
about that. Let’s talk through it. The probability
of an observation ending up in the jth interval
is just the probability that it is less than
or equal to the top of the interval, F of
c sub j, minus the probability that it is
less than or equal to the bottom of the interval,
F of c sub j minus 1. The pmf just writes
those formulas more generally. The likelihood
is equal to the product of all the probabilities
and the log-likelihood is just the natural
log of the likelihood, or the sum of the log
of the probabilities.
Back to censoring, suppose that X represents
a loss due to an insured event and that u
is a known censoring point. If observations
are censored from the right (or from above),
then we observe Y equals the minimum of X
and u and delta u is the indicator if x is
greater than or equal to u. If censoring occurs
so that delta u equals 1, then X is greater
than or equal to u and the likelihood is 1
minus F of u. If censoring does not occur
so that delta u equals 0, then X is less than
c sub u and the likelihood is f(y). In notation,
the likelihood is at the bottom of the slide.
Now that we have the likelihood for a single
observation, consider a random sample of size
n with a set of potential censoring times.
Then the joint likelihood is just the product
of the individual likelihoods, or the pdf
of y sub I for all the uncensored observations
times one minus the cdf of u sub i for all
the censored observations. Again, the log
likelihood is simply the natural log of the
likelihood.
Truncated data are handled in likelihood inference
via conditional probabilities. Adjust the
likelihood contribution by dividing by the
probability that the variable was observed.
Summarizing, we have the following contributions
to the likelihood for six types of outcomes
in the table at the bottom of the slide.
To combine the likelihoods, we simply multiply
each of the terms from our sample. We can
then take the derivative of the loglikelihood
and set it equal to zero to find the maximum
likelihood estimate.