Hello and welcome back. My name is Brian Hartman
and I am an associate professor at Brigham
Young University.
This slide reviews grouped data from the first
video in this section. If you would like to
review this slide, please pause the presentation
or go back to the earlier video.
Censoring occurs when we observe only a limited
value of an observation. Suppose that X represents
a loss due to an insured event and that u
is a known censoring point. If observations
are censored from the right (or from above),
then we observe Y equals the minimum of X
and u. In this case, u may represent the upper
limit of coverage for an insurer. The loss
exceeds the amount u but the insurer does
not have in its records the amount of the
actual loss. If observations are censored
from the left (or from below), then we observe
the maximum of X and u. Let u represents the
upper limit of coverage but now Y − u represents
the amount that a reinsurer is responsible
for. If the loss X is less than u, then Y
equals 0, no loss for the reinsurer. If the
loss X is greater than or equal to u, then
Y equals X – u and represents the reinsurer’s
retained claims.
In this case, you can use the Kaplan-Meier
estimator. Let t sub one through t sub c be
distinct points at which an event of interest
occurs, or non-censored losses, and let s
sub j be the number of events at time point
t sub j. Further, the corresponding “risk
set” is the number of observations that
are active at an instant just prior to t sub
j. Using notation, the risk set is R sub j
equals the sum of the indicators. With this
notation, the product-limit estimator of the
distribution function is as follows. Greenwood
in 1926 derived the formula for the estimated
variance.