Hello and welcome to chapter 4. My name is
Brian Hartman and I am an associate professor
at Brigham Young University.
There are times when you do not want to or
cannot make strong assumptions about the distribution
of a quantity of interest. In those situations,
we use nonparametric estimation, sometimes
called empirical estimation. All we need to
assume is that the observations come from
a random sample, or are independent and identically
distributed, or iid. We do not assume any
specific cdf F.
Some of the simplest nonparametric estimators
are the moment estimators. The kth raw moment
is the expected value of X to the k. We estimate
that moment using the sample average of x
to the k. The kth central moment is the expected
value of the quantity x minus the overall
population mean mu to the k. That is estimated
by the sample average of the kth power of
the difference between each observation and
the sample mean.
With no parametric assumptions about the distribution,
we can approximate it through the empirical
cumulative distribution function, which is
simply the proportion of observations less
than or equal to x for each x. When the random
variable is discrete, we can also estimate
the pmf by using the proportion of the sample
equal to x.
In this toy example, we can estimate the mean
by using the sample mean and get 19.7. We
can also estimate the second central moment
and get 31.01.
This plot shows the empirical cumulative distribution
function of the toy example. For each x, this
is the proportion of samples less than or
equal to x.
Back to our toy example, the median can be
any value between 20 and 23, though many software
packages use the average, in this case 21.5.
The smoothed empirical percentile uses linear
interpolation to estimate the quantiles between
samples.
To see how this works, we will find the 50th
and 20th quantiles in the toy example. The
computational details are on the slide, but
heuristically, the 50th quantile is exactly
between the 5th and 6th observations while
the 20th quantile is closer to the 2nd observation
than the 3rd, though in this case it does
not matter because those two observations
are the same.
When the data is discrete, we can estimate
the probability mass function by the proportion
of observations at each value. Alternatively,
you can group the observations into intervals
and then estimate the probability mass function
for each of those intervals using the sample
proportions.
Because empirically estimated pmfs can be
rather jagged and variable, they can be smoothed
using kernel density estimators. First, you
pick a bandwidth. If we are estimating the
probability mass function at x, any observation
within b of x will contribute to the probability
mass at x. The larger the bandwidth, the smoother
the function will be. Additionally, the uniform
kernel density estimator is an asymptotically
unbiased estimator of f of x.
More generally, you can use many different
types of kernels to estimate the density.
Some commonly used examples are described
on the slide here. Most software defaults
to the Gaussian kernel, but is easily changed.
We apply the kernel density estimator to the
distribution function like this. For illustration,
the uniform kernel will work like this.
Observations can be grouped into intervals.
The empirical CDF is still defined at the
boundaries in the usual way. Within each interval,
we can use the ogive which is the same linear
approximation we used before.
One interesting thing about the ogive is its
derivative is called the histogram and is
the same as the histograms that we plot to
get a basic understanding of the data.