all right so here we're going to expand on
one of the videos from the textbook and use it
to explore a little bit more what a bayesian prior
distribution is what a posterior distribution is
and what a predictive distribution is so getting
right to it we're going to look at example 4.4.5
this is an actuarial exam question and
here's what we're given the probability
that an insured has at least one loss in
any given year is p so that's our parameter
this is a bayesian problem so we're going
to focus on uh the prior distribution
for that one parameter and we're
told it's uniform between 0 and 0.5
but for one particular customer they've had
eight consecutive years of at least one loss
and we're asked to calculate the posterior
probability that that person will again have
another loss in year nine okay so just thinking
about it it seems like this particular customer
has a much higher probability of
giving losses we've seen eight in a row
we might really guess that they're likely to
have a ninth one and this is a classic example
of the power of bayesian methods so we'll start
with a little bit of notation i'm going to call
x i equal one the customer had at least one loss
in year i
and of course this parameter p sitting right
here is understood as the probability that
x i is equal to one okay so that's
the setup what are they asking me for
they're asking for the posterior probability
that this person will have a loss in year nine
the probability that x nine is equal to one given
they've had a loss every year for eight years okay
given that they had a loss in year one two three
four five six seven all the way through eight
this is what i'm being asked to find and
this is the posterior predictive distribution
why is that the posterior predictive
distribution well let's take a look at it
all of this information right here
x1 through x8 this is past theta
given i have observed that
what can i say about the future
what can i say about another unobserved
random variable okay so i take what i
know about the past and i'm somehow supposed to
use that to better inform a future prediction
and as the textbook shows the
definition of this thing of course
is the probability x 9 is equal
to 1 given i know the parameter p
times the probability of p given i know
eight years of loss data and i
integrate over the parameter p
okay this is the definition of the predictive
distribution and notice in particular we have
sitting right here the posterior distribution this
is my updated information about the parameter p
given i have observed eight years of data so let's
uh collect what we know so far we have a prior
distribution which was given to us in
the problem uniform between 0 and 0.5
the prior is pi p which is uniform between 0
and 0.5 i'm going to draw the prior over here
here's my parameter p start at zero this thing
is bounded at 0.5 and of course if it's uniform
what that means let's see what color should i use
for the prior the prior will henceforth be red
it is every value equally likely that's the prior
well then i have a customer with
eight years of consecutive losses
so i need to compute the posterior
this is pi of p given x1 is the loss
all the way through x8 is a loss
okay so we use what we know
about bayesian methods in general
this posterior of course is going to
be proportional to the probability
year one was a loss given p times year two
three four five six seven eight was a loss
times the prior
and of course this is p times times p
there are eight of them times the prior
which is 2. the posterior will
be proportional to p to the 8th
power and in the textbook it goes through
how to find the normalizing constant
because we know that the posterior is a density
and must integrate to 1. so in fact the posterior
is equal to nine times point five to the
negative ninth power times p to the eighth
all right let's take a look at that here
this by the way is the posterior and this is what
i'm going to plug in for the predictive density
and if this is proportional to p to the eighth
when p is small near zero this is going to be
very small and when p is larger this is going to
be larger the posterior looks something like this
and that makes sense because this person after
all has had eight consecutive years of losses
so probably for this person they have a much
larger probability of experiencing a loss they
just seem to be a riskier customer and so we
have finally uh set the table for solving the
problem that we need to solve we want to ask
ourselves what is the probability that this
person after eight years of losses will experience
at least one more loss next year all we need to do
now that we have our posterior is integrate
the probability of one more loss given p
times the posterior dp we need to
evaluate this predictive distribution
so doing that of course probability next year
is at least the loss given the last eight is the
integral 0 to 0.5 the probability of one
more loss given p times the posterior
dp
the probability of one more loss
that's just p the posterior is nine
times .5 to the negative ninth power times p to
the eighth and i integrate this over d over p
so we can move some constants out front i get
a nine times a point five to the negative ninth
power i have a p to the nine and i integrate
that so of course i get one over ten times p
to the tenth power and i evaluate this
expression between point five and zero
so we collect some terms i'll get the nine out
front bring the ten over of course i have point
five to the negative nine and that's going to be
multiplied by 0.5 to the 10. so only a 0.5 remains
then when i plug in 0 the
whole expression is equal to 0.
so this is 0.5 over times 9
over 10 which is equal to 0.45
and let's think about that number in
the context of the problem we've already
established this was a very risky customer
they've had eight consecutive years of losses
even though my prior distribution thought
the probability someone would get a loss
was evenly distributed between 0 and 0.5 for this
risky customer after 8 years of losses i'm pretty
sure their probability of a loss is much higher so
i calculate the bayesian predictive distribution
which is defined as we've shown and sure
enough we find the probability that this person
should experience yet another loss is on the
large side of this range is 0.45 so what we've
seen in this problem once again is how to move
from a prior belief updating that through data
to construct a posterior and now using that
posterior to move to a predictive distribution
to say something about what we think the next
observed variable might look like thank you