Hi, I'm Brian Hartman from Brigham Young University.
Today, we are going to be talking about tools
for model selection. In order to discuss this,
we're gonna use an example where we have some
data and we think, well, this data might come
from a gamma distribution, or it might come
from pareto distribution. How can we tell
which one it probably came from?
One way to start is to look at just the CDFs
and the PDFs and plot them on the same plot.
And so we see here on the left, the CDFs of
both the gamma and the pareto distribution
in addition to the data, which are the dots.
And you can see just by looking at it that
the gamma distribution that's this line right
here, doesn't seem to fit the data really
well. Whereas the pareto distribution, this
purple line right here, it seems to fit it
really well. You could also look at the density
functions or the PDFs. And again, we see that
the gamma PDF is not that close to the kernel
density estimate of the data, which is this
black line. Whereas the purple line, which
is the, the fitted Pareto is much closer.
So it seems pretty likely that the pareto
makes more sense.
One other way you can do this is something
called the P P plot. And this gives that empirical
CDF at each observation on the horizontal
axis. And so when you see that it seems to
fit really well like it does in the plot on
the right then most of these points are going
to be near the X equals Y line. As we see
with the gamma, we have this shape that obviously
doesn't fit that X equals Y line. So again,
this is more evidence that the Pareto was
probably a better fit to this data than the
gamma distribution.
We'd also look at a QQ plot, which does quantiles
instead of the probabilities. This also gives
us a little more information. So we see again,
looking at both the gamma quantile and the
log gamma quantile, that both of those are
pretty poor fits, but as we look at the Pareto
quantile, we see that on this log scale it
has a little bit of a hard time with these
smaller observations. It does much better
with the bigger observations.
We might want to add a little more structure
around this. While it's nice to look at pictures
and say, this picture seems to fit better
than the other. We might want to have some
kind of structure and an actual hypothesis
test. These are called goodness of fit tests.
The idea behind these tests is that we first
assume
that the distribution generated the data and
then we go looking for evidence that it didn't.
Our null hypothesis is the data did come from
that population. And our alternative is that
the data did not. And so if we get enough
evidence against that null hypothesis we're
gonna reject the hypothesis. And we say that
this model, or this distribution, is not a
good fit for this data.
One such goodness of fit test is called the
Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, the KS test. What
it does is it measures the max distance between
the empirical CDF and the CDF of the fitted
distribution. We can go back to our plots
here, and I can give you an example. So in
this case, if we were to do a test for the
gamma distribution, looking over here at the
CDFs, we would find the maximum distance between
the gamma CDF and the empirical CDF. And it
would be probably right here. And so that's
a pretty big difference. And maybe that would
mean that we reject that null hypothesis because
the difference was so big. Alternatively,
if we look at the Pareto fitted distribution,
we see that the maximum distance is probably
right here, but it's really, really small.
Maybe that's not enough evidence to reject
the null hypothesis. Maybe that would say
the Pareto is decent. That's why the KS test
looked at the maximum of these differences.
Here are some possible critical values that
you can look at. You can estimate any of these
probabilities or P values from any software
package.
Another one, if you have grouped data is the
Chi square test and the idea behind the Chi
square tests with group data, as we say, under
the model, we would expect to have X observations
in this group and Y observations in this group,
we actually have this and this, how close
are those expected observations to the actual
observations? So that's what this is right
here. Here is the number of observations in
category J minus the expected observations
in category J squared over the expected observations
in category J. Then you sum those all up for
all the categories. And you get a test statistic,
which is actually Chi squared distributed
with degrees of freedom equal to the number
of groups minus one minus R, which is the
number of groups or estimated parameters.
So that's another way that you can test whether
that distribution seems to fit well or not.
So we learned how to summarize data graphically.
We learned how to summarize through goodness
of fit tests. And we look forward to the next
section, which is likelihood ratio tests and
goodness of fit tests.