Hello and welcome back. My name is Brian Hartman
and I am an associate professor at Brigham
Young University.
One important type of inference is to select
one of two candidate models, where one model
(reduced model) is a special case of the other
model (full model). In a Likelihood Ratio
Test, we conduct the following hypothesis
test: H0: Reduced model is correct against
H1: Full model is correct.
To conduct the Likelihood Ratio Test we first
determine the maximum likelihood estimator
for full model, theta hat full. Then we assume
that p restrictions are placed on the parameters
of the full model to create the reduced model;
determine the maximum likelihood estimator
for the reduced model, theta hat reduced.
Two times the difference in log-likelihood
of the full and reduced models is the likelihood
ratio or LRT. Under the null hypothesis, the
likelihood ratio has a chi-square distribution
with degrees of freedom equal to p. Critical
value is a quantile from a chi-square distribution
with degrees of freedom equal to p - If LRT
is large relative to the critical value, then
we reject the reduced model in favor of the
full model.
The following statistics can be used when
comparing several candidate models that are
not necessarily nested (as in the Likelihood
Ratio Test). One picks the model that maximizes
the criterion. Note that these are one version
of the criterion, other versions may be multiplied
by two or may minimize a negative number,
but the relative order is what matter. Akaike’s
Information Criterion (AIC) is the log-likelihood
minus the number of parameters in the model.
The number of parameters term is a penalty
for the complexity of the model. Other things
equal, a more complex model means more parameters,
resulting in a smaller value of the criterion.
Similarly, to use a more complex model, there
must be a significant increase in the loglikelihood.
Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) is the
loglikelihood minus 0.5 times the number of
parameters times the number of observations.
This measure gives greater weight to the number
of parameters, resulting in a larger penalty.
Other things being equal, BIC will suggest
a simpler model than AIC.
As mentioned in the previous slide, here is
an alternative version of AIC and BIC where
you minimize the criterion. It is simply the
AIC and BIC values from the previous slide
multiplied by negative two.