Hello, I am Miyuki Ebisaki, a member of ASTIN
board.
Thank you for volunteered for this project,
a short course of Loss Data Analytics, which
forms a part of ASTIN Academy.
I would like to give a short explanation about
ASTIN, and what ASTIN would like to achieve
through ASTIN Academy.
ASTIN is a well-established worldwide leading
forum of risk and actuarial professionals
of non-life insurance industry. Created as
the first Section of the International Actuarial
Association (IAA) in 1957.
ASTIN has evolved and broadened its boundaries
to areas ranging from the well-established
Ratemaking and Reserving to more contemporary
Risk and Capital Management, and newly emerging
Data Science and Machine Learning.
This table shows how ASTIN plans to develop
actuarial education for audience of beginners
and professionals, with lectures given by
professionals and authorities.
We have held colloquia for fifty times in
sixty years. In recent years, we introduced
a series of specialised workshops, with the
aim of bridging the gap between academia and
industry.
ASTIN plans to produce a series of online
masterclasses on a wide range of non-life
insurance topics. The last but the most important
development is education for beginners conveyed
by authorities. It is ASTIN Academy to fill
in the missing piece.
The mission of the ASTIN Academy is to provide
high quality free educational materials in
non-life insurance to actuarial students across
the world. The Academy is committed to open
course development under Creative Commons
license and seeks innovation in teaching methodologies
and application of technology.
Let’s build the future of actuarial education
together.