Hi, I'm Paul Johnson.
I'm a lecturer in the
Wisconsin School of Business
at the University of
Wisconsin, Madison.
And I want to take a
couple of minutes to show
you how to navigate
this online tutorial,
exploring the foundations
of loss data analytics.
It is expected that it'll take
the average person
about six hours
to complete this tutorial.
But that's only an estimate.
You're encouraged to work through
this tutorial at your
own pace in a way that
allows you to fully
understand and be
able to apply the
concepts described here.
And I'll also say that
this tutorial does assume
some familiarity in our
statistical programming language.
And if you need to learn about
bad or get a
refresher about, are.
There are links in
this tutorial to
a data cap introduction
to R. Okay,
now as far as how to
actually navigate this,
if you look at the left,
you'll see a bunch of links
where if you focus here,
you could see that
this is chapter one,
introduction to LA
stayed analytics.
In time. There'll be
multiple chapters,
so there'll be a chapter to
chapter three and
so on and so forth.
But for each chapter
there'll be subsections.
And so when I am in right now is
Section 1.5 of chapter one,
which talks about property
find braiding variables.
So I'll use this
as an illustration
for what you'll do
in a subsection.
So the sub-section, we'll
start with video introduction,
in which some
individual will have
a short four to eight
minute video that
summarizes the key
learning objectives
for this subsection.
In this case, Professor freeze
will provide an overview
of raided variables for the
Wisconsin property fund.
Then, following the video,
there'll be one or
two exercises that
is related to what was
described in the video.
And each of these
exercises are done on
an online learning platform
by data camp so that
you don't need to actually
install R on your device.
I would encourage
you if you plan,
I do eat further analyses
beyond this tutorial with R,
that you do download
and install R and use
the code editor RStudio to
be able to work with that.
One of the advantages
of being able to have
already old computer
is you can work
with all kinds of
different R packages.
But for the purpose
of this tutorial,
you could just do
it exercise using
the R script that's provided
in a box like this.
Alright, so in this
particular exercise,
we are to modify the function
by var some to include
the standard
deviation and include
documentation of this
statistic in the table.
And so you'll see that there's
blanks in this script.
And in exercises like this,
you should fill in the
blanks with what you
think are appropriate R code.
And just to illustrate this,
I will type in.
So I'll take this and I will put
in STD for standard deviation,
put in an a four here.
And then I'll play it.
Not sure here.
And then what you could do
is you can run this code.
And if there are errors,
there'll be pointed out to you.
So in this line here,
I have this bar
that I apparently did it
needed to get rid of.
Okay. But what she could
do was then you can make
the change and you can redo
it and see if it works out.
And if you're ever stuck,
you can look for hints or you
can just see what
the solution is.
The idea is that you shouldn't
worry about making mistakes
because this is something
that you can do at your own pace.
The most important thing is
to be able to ultimately
enhance your understanding
about lost data analytics.
And just to be clear,
there are other
mistakes in this line
and in what I entered in
this particular exercise.
So I was just trying to give you
an idea of how this worked.
What do you actually
do this exercise,
you'll be able to be a bit more
thoughtful in filling
in the blanks.
And I was for this illustration.
Thanks for watching this video.
I'm navigating this
online tutorial.