Welcome back to this video on an Introduction
to Analytics.
Hi, my name is Paul Johnson. I am a lecturer
in the Wisconsin School of Business at the
University of Wisconsin-Madison.
And in this video, I am going to introduce
the Wisconsin Property Fund, an example that
we will be using throughout this course.
OVERHEAD 1 - Wisconsin Property Fund
In the US State of Wisconsin, the insurance
regulator, known as the Office of the Insurance
Commissioner, administers an insurance pool
for state and local government agencies. The
pool is called the Local Government Property
Insurance Fund, sometimes known through the
acronym LGPIF, and that we will call the Wisconsin
Property Fund.
This fund has offered since 1911 and provides
insurance on property such as government buildings,
schools, libraries, and motor vehicles.
The policyholders in the fund consist of over
a thousand local government entities that
include counties, cities, towns, villages,
school districts, and library boards.
OVERHEAD 2 - LGPIF Policyholder A
These policyholders are not people but rather
government agencies. So, this is fund is closer
to commercial insurance, or insurance for
businesses, rather than personal insurance
which is insurance for people.
Just to get a feel for what we are insuring,
here is the first of two examples. This is
a picture of an elementary school building
which is part of a school district.
Specifically, it is part of the Madison Metropolitan
School District that has 98 buildings, 18
major pieces of equipment, and 630 properties
in the open. The open properties include benches,
playsets, goals, and so forth. The insured
value of the property is $640 millions of
USD.
OVERHEAD 3 - LGPIF Policyholder B
But, the Madison Metropolitan School District
is not the largest of the approximately one
thousand insureds. That honor goes to the
city of Green Bay that has insured value of
approximately $2.4 billions of USD. Of its
118 sites, here is a picture of Lambeau Field.
This is the stadium in which a professional
American football team, the Green Bay Packers,
plays.
Interestingly, because of its world-wide reknown,
the fund has a separate terrorism reinsurance
coverage for this property.
OVERHEAD 4 - Property Fund
To give you a feel for the size, the fund
receives approximately $25 million in premiums
each year and provides insurance coverage
for about $75 billion.
The fund offers three major groups of insurance
coverage: building and contents, construction
equipment, and motor vehicles.
For building and contents, the fund covers
all property losses except those resulting
from flood, earthquake, wear and tear, extremes
in temperature, mold, war, nuclear reactions,
and embezzlement or theft by an employee.
OVERHEAD 5 - Claims Frequency - R Code
Now that we have described a meaningful business
context, let's move directly to the analytics.
We want to show how statistical code can be
used to provide some useful results for understanding
the business of insurance.
Here are 4 lines of code.
In the first, we read in the the data, externally
stored in a "csv", for "comma-separated-value"
format, into an internal data frame, in this
case called "Insample".
Next, we restrict attention to a subset of
year 2010 experience. It is common to examine
insurance data on a yearly basis to separate
the investigation of trends.
In the last two lines, we summarize the data.
Instead of showing the direct result from
these commands, in the next overhead we present
the output in a format one might use to make
business decisions.
OVERHEAD 6 - Claims Frequency (2010)
From the frequency table, we learn several
things. For example, the table shows 1,110
policyholders who have 1,377 claims. Of these
claims, almost two-thirds of the policyholders
did not have any claims, 18.8% had one claim
and remaining 17.5% had more than one claim.
From the summary statistics, we learn that
one policyholder with the highest number recorded
239 claims. Further digging shows that this
was the Madison Metropolitan School district.
Many of these claims were from minor damage
such as broken windows caused by misbehaving
children. Further, the average number of claims
for this sample was 1.24.
REVIEW
This provide just a brief glimpse of the data.
But, let's pause for a moment to give you
time to practice the tools introduce so far.
I hope that you found this overview of Wisconsin
Property Fund to be useful.
In this video, we examined the frequency of
claims for the fund. In the next video, you
will learn how to analyze claim amounts, also
known as the severity of claims.
Thanks for watching!