Welcome back to the tutorial on an Introduction
to Loss Data Analytics.
Hello, my name is Jed Frees, an emeritus professor
at the University of Wisconsin and the Australian
National University. In this video, I am going
to demonstrate how different characteristics
may affect our assessment of insurance costs
in the context of the Wisconsin Property Fund.
OVERHEAD 1 - Description of Rating Variables
Here is a list of available characteristics;
hopefully, these are variables that you think
might naturally be related to claims outcomes.
It is common to refer to these as rating variables.
Conceptually, these variables may affect the
distribution of insurance outcomes that we
have discussed, the frequency and severity.
As they affect these claims distributions,
they affect estimates of insurance costs and
so our determination of rates that one pays
for insurance.
The two approximately continuous variables
are coverage and deductibles.
To handle their skewness, we focus on logarithmic
transformations. Most rating variables employed
in the analysis of insurance claims are of
the categorical type. Here, we have entity
type, type of credit for smoke alarm, as well
as indicators for no claim credit and presence
of a fire station. In our analysis, we focus
on the categorical variables.
OVERHEAD 2 - Claims by Entity Type, Fire Class,
and No Claim Credit
Here are some summary statistics by three
of the four categorical variables, with alarm
credit being deferred to later. As before,
we present simple averages to get a quick
idea of differences in the distributions.
The first thing to notice from the table is
that there is substantial variation in the
frequency and severity by entity type. This
is intuitively plausible; for example, we
expect more claims for small villages in comparison
to larger counties. This will imply very different
costs of insurance by entity types.
As anticipated, we see both lower frequency
and lower severity when the policyholder had
no claims in the past two years, so that NoClaimCredit
indicator is 1. This is also common in the
analysis of insurance claims, past experience
is often an excellent predictor of current
and future behavior.
Somewhat surprising is the higher frequency
and severity for the Fire5 (=1) variable.
This is counter-intuitive in that one would
expect lower claim amounts for those policyholders
in areas with better public protection (when
the protection code is five or less). There
are at least two possible explanations for
this. One is that policyholders who greater
public protection nearby become more careless.
The second is that there may be a joint effect
that is being masked by our univariate analysis.
For example, it could be that there are many
more Fire5=1 policyholders that are counties
and we have already seen that counties are
more risky compared to other entities. So,
the Fire5=1 variable effect is being distorted
by another variable. Or, it may be that areas
with better public protection are naturally
higher risk areas; the protection is there
because it is thought to be needed and we
have no other variable that indicates this
need.
This emphasizes a major drawback of this type
of presentation. These tables look at the
effects of each variable in isolation of the
others and so are referred to as a "univariate"
analyses. As another example, you may have
seen "simple linear regression" in your other
studies. In any case, you will find any type
of univariate analysis to be very convenient
because it is simple to execute and easy to
explain to others. However, it is limiting
in that does not permit an understanding of
the joint effects of variables.
OVERHEAD 3 - Claims by Entity Type, Fire Class,
and No Claim Credit - R Code
Here is the R code for this analysis.
As in prior examples, we used the "subset"
function to split the data set into smaller
pieces of interest and then used the "summaryBy"
function to pull out the relevant summary
statistics.
Because we were interested in so many statistics,
a small function was created to automate the
tasks.
OVERHEAD 4 - Claims by Entity Type and Alarm
Credit Category
Here is an analysis of the fourth categorical
variable, Alarm Credits.
When you take a look at the totals by entity,
we see the same counter intuitive results
as we did for the fire protection code. For
example, we would expect to see lower frequency
and severity for 15% alarm credits compared
to no alarm credits.
In this analysis, we attempted to dig a little
deeper by showing results by entity type.
To illustrate, from this table, we can compare
villages by different levels of alarm credits.
Again, for example, comparing 15% to no alarm
credits, we again see the same counter-intuitive
results. Villages with 15% alarm credits actually
experience higher frequency and severity compared
to villages without alarm credits.
As before, the explanation could be that we
are missing a hidden variable that causes
this behavior. Or, it could be that managers
who purchase expensive alarm systems become
careless and suffer more accidents as a result.
OVERHEAD 5 -Initiating Insurance
These are the types of considerations that
come into play when trying to estimate the
cost of insurance that is needed to set insurance
rates.
As we have already seen, we have to take care
in choosing the time frame for our data. Based
on the 2010 data, we saw that the average
claim is 33,026. However, if we use 2009 data,
we arrive at a very different conclusion,
9,934.
From the analysis in this video, we see that
the distribution of claim outcomes varies
tremendously by entity type. So, knowing whether
a policyholder is a village, city, or so on
is an important determinant of the cost of
insurance. Although we haven't done the analysis
here, you can make a similar case for coverage.
It makes sense that larger risks should have
larger insurance costs.
What makes less sense is how to handle alarm
credits. If we follow the same logic, then
we would estimate the cost of insurance to
be smaller for an insured without an alarm
credit compared to one that has one. This
is really bad - we want to encourage insureds
to invest in protection of their risks. They
should not be discouraged from purchasing
alarm systems by paying more for insurance.
This is just one of the really interesting
questions that we will be able to discuss
as we develop our understanding of insurance
analytics.
REVIEW
I hope that you found this case study on the
Wisconsin Property Fund to be useful. In this
section, we learned how to:
☻ Describe how insurance events can produce
data of interest to analysts.
☻ Produce relevant summary statistics for
each variable.
☻ Describe how these summary statistics
can be used to develop the cost of insurance.
For this case study, we raise a number of
very interesting questions about how to estimate
the cost of insurance. Many students will
be surprised that we did not give answers
to these questions. We raised these questions
in part because they are real issues that
insurers deal with regularly and often there
is no clean answer. However, a solid discussion
of these issues rests on a good understanding
of the analytics of insurance claims. And
this is the focus of this course.
Thanks for watching!
(about 1200 words)