Welcome back to the tutorial on an Introduction
to Loss Data Analytics.
Hello, my name is Yvonne Cheuh. In this video,
I am going to demonstrate analytics of severity
distributions for the Wisconsin Property Fund.
OVERHEAD 1 - Severity Distribution (2010)
In the prior video on frequency of claims,
we learned that of the 1110 policyholders
in 2010, 707 did not experience any claims.
This means that 403, which is 1110 minus 707,
policyholders had at least one claim.
When examining the severity, or the amount,
of claims, there are at least two basic approaches.
One approach is to follow each claim and use
this information to get a sense of the distribution.
Another approach, taken here, is to follow
each policyholder. The drawback of following
a policyholder is that we typically no longer
have information about individual claims,
only the sum of claims attributable to a policyholder.
To make information among policyholders comparable,
it is customary to examine the average claim
for each policyholder. To illustrate, 209
policyholders had only one claim. Here, the
average claim is the single recorded claim.
In contrast, for example the average claim
for the Madison Metropolitan School District
is the average over 209 different recorded
events.
With this as background, the table displayed
shows summary statistics for the 403 average
claims. From this table, one immediately notices
that the maximum claim is over $12 million
USD. This unusually large amount is from a
real event (a flood in a Milwaukee courthouse)
and is very financially important to the fund.
In other areas of statistics, one might think
of this as an "outlier" and so a candidate
of removal from the rest of the data set.
However, in insurance statistics, unusually
large events and skewed distributions are
common, not the exception.
For example, take a look at the distribution
plotted on the left-hand side. This histrogram
is not really helpful for the analyst because
it is dominated by the extreme large value,
causing all the observations to be clustered
together on the left. One approach is to remove
this large point, at least for plotting purposes.
However, this does not help as other observations
take on a similar role. As an alternative,
it is common to plot logarithmic values, as
done in the right-hand panel. This graphs
gives use a much better sense of the severity
distribution.
OVERHEAD 2 - Claims Severity - R Code
So that you can replicate these results, here
is a look at the R code.
As with our frequency analysis, the first
two lines show how to bring in the data and
produce a data frame based on only 2010 information.
The third line creates a new data frame, InsamplePos2010,
that takes a subset of policyholders with
a positive average severity. You can check
that there are 403 policyholders with the
"length" command. The "summary" command produces
the table of summary statistics.
The rest of the code produces the two histograms
that we looked at. This is very handy because
we often want to compare phenomena graphically.
The "mfrow" syntax produces a figure with
1 row and 2 columns.
OVERHEAD 3 - Claim Outcomes and Coverage by
Year
We have seen analytics of frequency and severity
for 2010, so now let's take a look at trends
over years. One could produce distributions
over the years but, to begin, we look to simpler
averages. In the following display, we also
include the coverage. This plus the number
of policyholders gives a sense of the overall
exposure of the fund.
From the table, we see that the average frequency
is stable over the years, certainly in comparison
with the severity. As we might guess from
the analysis of a single year for the severity,
it tends to be volatile and is sensitive to
the impact of potentially large obsevations.
Both exposure measures indicate stability
over this time period. The coverage is slightly
increasing and the number of policyholders
slightly decreasing.
OVERHEAD 4 - Analysis by Year - R Code
Here is some R code that produces the results.
This uses the "summaryBy" function in the
package "doBy". Although a lot of this course
is learning by doing combined with replicating
examples, you will also want to get into the
habit of looking up the documentation for
functions that you might use. This function
also uses a function internally that we created,
labelled as "FUN1".
You will see more code like this as we go
forward, so I won't go over all the details
now. But, note that as a result, we produced
the data frame "Table1In". Then, we used the
"names" function to give lables for each column
- this is very handy way of keeping track
of elements.
OVERHEAD 5 - Claim Frequency and Severity,
Deductibles, and Coverage
For a different look at the 2006-2010 data,
this table summarizes the distribution of
our two outcomes, frequency and claims amount.
In each case, the average exceeds the median,
suggesting that the two distributions are
right-skewed. In addition, the table summarizes
our continuous rating variables, coverage
and deductible amount. The table also suggests
that these variables also have right-skewed
distributions.
OVERHEAD 6 - Claim Frequency and Severity,
Deductibles, and Coverage - R Code
Here is the R code used to produce this table.
Note that again we used the "SummaryBy" function
even though there way "By" part - this was
done just so that you can see another application
of this function. Also a little different
- the output from the function was converted
from a data frame to numbers using the "as.numeric"
function. This was done so that the outputs
could be combine into a matrix that allows
for easier display of row and column names.
You will see that R gives users quite a bit
of flexibility. There is more than one way
to accomplish an end goal.
OVERHEAD 7 - Cost of Insurance
To wrap up this video on claims analytics,
I want to briefly mention some thoughts on
how a claims distribution can be used to determine
the cost of insurance. I first note that the
Wisconsin property fund is a pool of government
entities. Unlike commercial insurers, it does
no underwriting and coverage cannot be denied.
This makes our job of assessing the cost of
insurance a bit easier - we can treat experience
from all policyholders as representative of
the pool of interest.
Now, to determine the cost of insurance, if
we make a decision based only on 2010 data,
we might use 33,026.
This number was determined by dividing the
total payout, the total fund claims, by the
number of policyholders.
However, we get a very different answer based
on 2009 data (it turns out to be 9,934). This
can be attributed to the volatility of the
claims distributions.
Moreover, having a single price for all policyholders
is nice but hardly seems fair. Should small
government libraries be charged the same as
the city of Green Bay? In the next video,
we introduce the basics of rating variables,
designed to put the costs among different
entities on a more equitable footing.
Thanks for watching!