Welcome to the tutorial on an Introduction
to Loss Data Analytics.
My name is Yvonne Chueh. I am a professor
at Central Washington University. Today, I
am going to discuss some key points on the
relevance of analytics.
In this course and book, we are considering
risk management and insurance techniques,
so I want to emphasize the importance of insurance.
OVERHEAD 1 - Relevance of Insurance
Insurance is an important economic activity.
A common method for measuring the extent of
activity is to examine the insurance premiums.
By this measure, insurance related activities
comprise about 6.3% of world GDP, or gross
domestic product. As one example, the country
with the highest percentage is Japan, where
insurance premiums accounted for 11.2% of
GDP. As another example, in the US insurance
actities accounted for 7.5% of GDP.
Without going into details, insurance is important
for businesses and governments.
On an individual level, insurance touches
the lives of most people. For example, almost
everyone owning a home has insurance to protect
themselves in the event of a fire, hailstorm,
or some other calamitous event. As another
example, almost every country requires some
type of insurance for those driving a car.
OVERHEAD 2 - Analytics and Loss Data
Because insurance is a big business, it is
not surprising that insurers employ analytics
in the same manner as other large corporations.
Virtually every large firm uses analytics
extensively in sales and marketing, compensation
and productivity analysis, as well as financial
forecasting. For example, in sales and marketing,
analytics is used to:
☻ Predict customer behavior/needs
☻ Anticipate customer reactions to promotions/rate
changes
☻ Manage acquisition costs such as online
sales.
Firms use analytics extensively and it is
highly likely that your role in a firm will
involve analytics in some capacity.
So, we could introduce analytics from one
of many perspectives, for example sales data
or returns on investments. In this course,
to keep a firm tie to the insurance industry,
we focus on loss data, also known as insurance
claims or insurance amounts.
OVERHEAD 3 - What is Analytics?
All firms use analytics, and insurers are
no exception. Moreover, insurance is a data-driven
industry, meaning that analytics is particularly
important. Analytics is a key to deriving
information from data.
But what precisely do we mean when say analytics?
For contrast, we might use
☻ "business intelligence". An old phrase
used by those in operations research. Here,
the focus is on processes of collecting data,
often through databases and data warehouses.
Or, we could use
☻ "business analytics", a description used
by many modern business schools. It suggests
utilizing tools and methods for statistical
analyses of data. Another is
☻ "data science", used by many departments
of statistics. This can encompass broader
applications in many scientific domains.
For our purposes, we use the term "Analytics"
to mean simply the process of using data to
make decisions.
Specifically, this process involves gathering
data, understanding models of uncertainty,
making general inferences, and communicating
results.
OVERHEAD 4 - Insurance Processes
We will be using insurance data to introduce
analytics and so it is helpful to think about
how this data is generated by insurance processes.
In a “micro” oriented view, we can think
specifically about what happens to a contract
at various stages of its existence. Here is
a graph that symbolizes the timeline of a
typical insurance policy.
It marks when a policy starts with a premium
payment. Policies that we focus on, such as
motor vehicle, are typically short-term contracts
such as 6 months or a year but that also typically
are renewed, resulting in another premium
payment. Also marked on the graph are claim
occurrences, and there may be more than one
of them even within a single short-term period.
REVIEW
I hope that you found this overview of the
relevance of analytics to be useful. In this
section, we learned how to:
☻ Summarize the importance of insurance
to consumers and the economy
☻ Describe analytics
☻ Identify data generating events associated
with the timeline of a typical insurance contract
Thanks for watching.