Welcome back to the tutorial on an Introduction
to Loss Data Analytics.
Hello, my name is Jed Frees, an emeritus professor
with University of Wisconsin and Australian
National University. In this video, I am going
to discuss some key points on insurance company
operations.
OVERHEAD 1 - Insurance Company Operations
In the prior video, we discussed how claims
data are likely to come from the lifetime
of a policy. For analysts, it is also important
to see how these data may be used in the firm
operations.
From an Insurer’s viewpoint, to operate
they need ways of bringing money in, paying
it out, managing costs, and making sure that
the insurer has enough money to meet obligations.
To make this happen, insurers aggregate detailed
insurance processes into larger operational
units. Here is a list of the five units commonly
used within the insurance industry.
The first unit is about when the insurers
initiates the policy. Here, analysts are involved
in determining an appropriate price for a
risk. Before the pricing, risks are grouped
into appropriate categories that are similar
to one another. "Adverse selection" is a common
phenomena in insurance such as has a policyholder
with a risky tendency, like a history of alcoholism,
that the insurer is unaware of. Identifying
adverse selection is an important component
of pricing risks.
Pricing is also important at the renewal of
insurance. Many personal insurance contracts,
such as auto and homeowners, have relatively
short terms such as 6 months or a year but
are typically renewed. In this way, the effective
length of the relationship between policyholder
and insurer is much longer than the contract
term and insurers want to retain customers
deemed profitable.
OVERHEAD 2 - Insurance Company Operations
Pricing is most visibile to the public but
an equally important part of insurance company
operations is paying, and managing, claims.
Insurers use analytics for early identification
of costly claims so they can field the appropriate
teams to pay, and in some cases, litigate
responsibility for claims. They also use analytics
to manage mischief, as fraud can raise costs
for all parties.
Another unit of insurance operations is that
of setting aside money for future obligations,
a process known as reserving. Medical costs
associated with some lines of business such
as workers compensation can take many years
to evolve. As another example, claims that
associatied general obligations and liabilities
of firms can also take many years to evolve
due to extensive legal activities. These are
two examples where analysts
☻ Predict future obligations
☻ Quantify the uncertainty of the estimates
☻ Match projections of obligations to income
streams
The fifth and final operational unit regards
determining the amount of money to be held
to keep an insurer financial stability, the
solvency, and the business units that can
most productively use the money, capital allocation.
Analysts in this domain work to decide appropriate
level of necessary capital and to help manage
external stakeholders’ expectations.
OVERHEAD 3 - Operations – Initiating Insurance
Analysts work extensively with pricing insurance
at the initial contract. The public cares
about pricing and so this is the focus of
our introduction to insurance analytics.
But, setting the price of an insurance good
can be a perplexing problem. We are bit more
familiar with pricing in other sectors. For
example,
☻ In manufacturing, the cost of a good is
(relatively) known, making pricing simpler.
☻ In other areas of financial services,
market prices are available.
In many lines of insurance, start with an
expected cost, add “margins” to account
for the product’s riskiness, expenses incurred
in servicing the product, and a profit/surplus
allowance for the insurance company.
with this structure, getting the expected
cost is a key ingredient. Especially in automobile
and homeowners insurance, analytics to sharpen
the market by making the calculation of the
distribution more precise.
In this course, we build the foundations.
Later, you will see that multivariate pricing
strategies routinely employ advanced statistical
methods such as generalized linear modeling.
OVERHEAD 4 - Big Data
Much of the gain in popularity in advancing
analytics in the recent years is due to increased
willingness to use data to make business decisions.
Some call this movement "Big Data," referring
to the increasing capacity and computational
abilities of computers, availability of new
and innovative sources of data, and advanced
algorithms that can detect patterns in insurance
activities that were previously unknown.
Traditionally, insurers used only information
reported by policyholders on application forms,
combined with selected external sources. For
example, for decades auto insurers used police
reports to price automobile insurance and
medical exam results for life insurance.
Now, there is interest in collecting more
information about policyholders. Some credit
the interest in using more and different data
to Progressive Insurance who used credit scores
for pricing automobile insurance. From an
analyst’s viewpoint, these additional sources
have proven to be significant from predictive
and economic viewpoints.
There are serious questions as what types
of data are ethically permissible for insurers
to use. For example, it has long been held
that use of racial and ethnic information
is illegal in most jurisdictions. The resulting
debates are important.
Our position is not that analysts should dictate
whether or not use of information should be
restricted or prohibited. Rather, these considerations
involve policy choices that should also involve
legal and economic scholars, as well as government
representatives and advocates for the industry
and for consumers. Analysts can make important
contributions to these discussions by quantifying
the financial impact of policy alternatives.
REVIEW
I hope that you found this overview of insurance
company operations to be useful. In this section,
we learned how to:
☻ Describe five major operational areas
of insurance companies.
☻ Identify the role of data and analytics
opportunities within the pricing area.
Thanks for watching!
(963 Words)