Hello! I am Shyamal Kumar from the Department of
Statistics and Actuarial Science at the University
of Iowa. This lecture concerns the maximum
likelihood method for frequency distributions.
We are considering the following problem:
we have a random sample from some unknown
count distribution, and we wish to
make informed data-driven decisions.
Typically, an indexed set of distributions is
assumed to contain the unknown distribution,
with the index commonly
referred to as the parameter.
In this setup, making good decisions reduces
to arriving at a good data-driven guess
for the parametric value, say theta_0, that
corresponds to the underlying distribution.
Two simplifying features of the statistical
estimation problem described above are that
the observations are non-negative integers
and the parameter space is a Euclidean subset.
When working with count data of size n,
a basic summary is the frequency table.
The frequency table can be seen as a sequence
m_k, for non-negative integral values of k,
with m_k denoting the number
of observations equal to k.
While there can be at most n non-zero
m_k's, typically, there are far fewer.
For example, when sampling
from a binomial distribution,
there are at most m-plus-one many non-zero
m_k's regardless of the sample size n.
A natural question that arises is if this
summarization in terms of the frequency table
comes at the cost of loss of statistical
information - the answer is no. This conclusion
derives from either the likelihood principle or
the sufficiency principle. In the next slide,
we present the argument using
the likelihood principle.
Towards stating the likelihood principle,
we note that the likelihood function for a
random sample is the product of the probability
mass function evaluated at the sample points,
viewed as a function of the unknown parameter.
The likelihood principle states that all
the information relevant to the statistical
inference of the unknown parameter is
contained in the likelihood function.
The shown alternate expression for
the likelihood in terms of m_ks
alone implies the lossless compression
that the frequency table affords.
The maximum likelihood estimation method posits
that the arg max of the likelihood function is a
compelling estimator for the unknown parameter.
To illustrate this method, consider a simple model
consisting of two probability mass functions,
with common support consisting
of only three and five.
p_1 assigns a probability of 0.8 to three,
whereas p_2 allocates a probability of only 0.4.
Also, consider a sample of size three consisting
of observations equal to three, three, and five.
The likelihood is a function defined on the set
containing 1 and 2, with L(1) equal to 0.128
and L(2) equal to 0.096. Since
the likelihood is maximized at 1,
the maximum likelihood estimate
for the unknown parameter is 1.
Often it is easy to work with the logarithm of
the likelihood, the so-called log-likelihood.
Towards understanding the reason behind its
use, we note that the logarithm is a strictly
increasing function on the positive half of
the real line, the range of the likelihood
function. The former implies that the arg max
of the log-likelihood coincides with the MLE.
On the theoretical side, since
maximization often involves
differentiation, working with the log-likelihood
automatically drops the likelihood factors
that are free of the parameter
on taking the first derivative.
This property offers much pedagogic ease
and hence is pervasively used in texts.
On the numerical side, since the likelihood decays
exponentially with sample size n, working with the
log-likelihood offers numerical stability by
reducing the impact of floating-point errors.
The displayed graph contains the plots
in black of a likelihood function
and its log-likelihood function in red.
Notice that they have the same domain
and are maximized at the same
parametric value of 2.85.
In the following two exercises,
you will implement two different data
structures to store the frequency table,
which will give you a first-hand experience of
the data compression we have alluded to above.
Thank you!