Hello!
I am Shyamal Kumar from the Department of
Statistics and Actuarial Science at the University
of Iowa. This lecture concerns extensions of
the (a,b,0) class of frequency distributions.
Recall that the (a,b,0)-class of count
distributions consists of three distributions:
Binomial, Poisson, and Negative Binomial.
While these cater well to many modeling needs,
actuaries need more distributions in practice.
To begin with, the (a,b,0)
being a two-parameter family
is a small subset of the infinite-dimensional
set of all count distributions.
So the need for more distributions in the
actuarial tool kit should come as no surprise.
The following slides concern two natural
reasons for extending the (a,b,0)-class.
In a mathematical sense, these extensions
are actuarially driven closure requirements
on the set of distributions in an actuarial tool
kit. This latter point will become apparent soon.
Actuaries often encounter heterogeneity at
the population level. A modeling technique
is to divide the population into
homogeneous sub-populations.
Actuaries commonly do so for risk
rating, among other reasons.
(a,b,0)-class of distributions often works well
at the sub-population level, even if not at the
population level. For example, two distinct
binomially distributed sub-populations
do not lead to a binomially
distributed population.
The extension this prompts is explained
graphically in the next slide.
Consider a portfolio of policies consisting
of two sub-portfolios with their number of
policies in the ratio of 2:1. Their respective
distributions of claims per policy are binomials
with parameter m equal to two and parameter q
equal one-fourth and two-thirds, respectively.
Distributions with support consisting of
counts zero, one, and two are defined by the
probabilities they assign to one and two, which
allows us to plot them on a graph as shown here.
The plotted curve, in black, represents all
binomials with parameter m equal to two,
and the red dots represent the two binomials
corresponding to the two sub-portfolios.
A simple calculation shows
that the green dot represents
the count distribution of a randomly
selected policy from this portfolio.
Notice that since it does not lie on the
curve, it is not a binomial distribution.
This example conveys the need for all the
distributions represented by the points in
the shaded region interior to the curve,
the mixtures of the binomials with m=2.
We saw an actuarial motivation to round out
the distributions in the actuarial tool chest
by including their mixtures. Mathematically,
a mixture distribution is a convex combination
of its components, with their number being either
finite or infinite. Section 2.5 discusses
the mechanics of working with mixtures.
We now present another natural
extension of a set of distributions.
Employers provide insurance coverage
to their employees in many countries,
leading to redundant coverage for working couples.
As a result, a proportion of insureds may not
file any claims on some of their policies.
Such market realities,
among others, create an out-sized proportion of
zero claims which is ill-fitted by the standard
parametric families of distributions,
including those of the (a,b,0) class.
Modifying a probability mass
function p as shown here,
with the resulting probability of zero counts
equal to q0, is called its zero-modification.
And such modifications extend a set of
distributions by adding the extra parameter
q0, enabling accommodation of
any probability for zero counts.
Moreover, the zero-modification specified
aligns with the insurance market realities.
Zero-modification of a distribution, with q0 equal
to 0, results in its zero-truncated version. In
other words, the zero-truncated version
is the conditional distribution of counts
given at least one count, which is of
independent actuarial interest as well.
A noteworthy feature of zero modification is that
the ratio of successive probabilities beyond zero
remains unchanged. The identical
shifts of the probabilities beyond zero
in the log-plot of the probability mass
functions of zero-modified versions
from its underlying confirms the above invariance.
An (a,b,0) distribution satisfies the displayed
recurrence for values of k starting from zero.
The invariance described in the previous
slide implies that a zero-modified version
of an (a,b,0) distribution satisfies the same
recurrence but for values beginning from one.
The (a,b,1) class of distributions consists
of those that satisfy the above recurrence
for values beginning from one.
This class is parameterized by p0, a, and b, with
p1 chosen to make the total probability one.
Clearly, modified versions of (a,b,0)
distributions belong to the (a,b,1)-class.
A natural question to ask is if all of the members
of the (a,b,1) class are zero-modified
versions of (a,b,0) distributions.
To answer this question, we note that when a is
positive, the constraint on b is dependent on the
lowest value of k at which the recurrence relation
holds. So when we move from (a,b,0) to (a,b,1),
the constraint relaxes from a+b>0 to
a+b/2>0, which enlarges the parameter space.
This enlargement allows for zero modified
versions of extended truncated negative binomials
and logarithmic distribution. These are not
zero-modified versions of (a,b,0) distributions.
In the exercise below, you would
get to test your understanding
of the (a,b,1) class of distributions.
Thank you!