Alright, so in this tutorial.
We've been asked to fit a Poisson density
to claims data using the method of maximum
likelihood estimation.
So here we will quickly review how to estimate
the mean parameter of a Poisson, using the
method of maximum likelihood estimation.
Going to the problem.
Okay.
We're deriving the maximum likelihood estimator
from the Poisson. So the starting point here
is to make sure we have the probability mass
function for a Poisson random variable probability
mass function. f of x equals e to the minus
lambda --- and that's
our parameter we will be estimating --- lambda
to the x, divided by x-factorial.
But we always want to be in the habit of giving
the permissible ranges of these parameters.
This parameter lambda has to be greater than
zero.
And the support
takes integer values, unbounded.
So that's the complete, mathematically thorough
way of writing the probability mass function.
Now we imagine that we've observed a sample
x-one through x-n.
And we need to construct the likelihood function,
which is the function we will maximize to
produce the maximum likelihood estimate.
So here, recall the definition of the likelihood
function.
It's a function of our parameter, and all
of our observations.
This is the joint probability mass function.
All n random variables...
Based on the parameter lambda.
But if we assume that our sample is independent.
We know the joint probability mass function
can be written as the product i goes from
one to n of the marginal probability mass
functions f of x-i, and lambda.
And this of course is made true by independence.
So to complete this likelihood
all we have to do is take a product of N of
these terms, we get the product i goes from
one to n, e to the negative lambda, lambda
to the x-i, divided by x-i factorial.
So, let's treat this as three distinct terms
--- we have, e to the minus lambda.
Then we have lambda to the x-i, then downstairs
and the denominator we have x-i factorial.
So if each of these probability mass functions
contributes an e to the negative lambda
when I multiply n of them, I will be left
with an e to the minus n times lambda.
Then of course I have a bunch of terms lambda
to the x-one times lambda to the x-two times
lambda to the x-three and so on.
We have the common base.
So, these combine to give lambda, and I will
simply add up the xs.
And then finally, we have this term downstairs.
We're just going to leave it alone.
I can... I'm seeing into the future, we can
leave this term alone, because it does not
involve the parameter lambda, so don't waste
a lot of time and energy, seeing if you can
simplify this expression, it will all become
moot.
So downstairs I will simply keep the product.
I equals one to N of x-i factorial.
And that is my likelihood function.
And I suppose I should remind everyone that
lambda is greater than zero.
So finally, we derive the maximum likelihood
estimator.
This is the value, which will maximize the
likelihood function.
So we take a derivative, we set that derivative
equal to zero and we solve for the parameter.
But the trick with these problems is it's
often easier
to maximize the log likelihood.
I'm going to call the log likelihood lowercase
L.
It's a function of my parameter.
It's equal to the logarithm of capital L.
So if I take the logarithm of this likelihood
function I've got three terms in here it's
where it's useful to remind ourselves of the
rules for logarithms.
Maybe I'll put those over here.
Recall that the log of A times B divided by
C is the log of A plus the log of B minus
the log of C,
that's the first rule we're going to remind
ourselves of. The second... that looks like
a minus sign and I really shouldn't do that
we'll make it a bullet point...
The second rule is that the log of D. to the
Eth power is equal to E times log D. These
two rules will come in handy.
So if I want to take the logarithm of this
whole function.
What I'm imagining here is that
this term in the beginning is A.
And then next...
This term
is B.
And finally, The denominator
is C.
So when I calculate this logarithm.
I'm going to get log A plus log B minus log
C, let's see how that simplifies, I get log
of the first term.
And I can bring that exponent down, minus
n lambda times the log of e, which is just
one,
plus the log of the second term, which gives
me the sum of x-i times the log of lambda.
I'm using this second rule down here.
And then I get minus the log of this messy-looking
term.
Okay, now that we have to log likelihood we
maximize that. So we take the derivative,
and we said it equal to zero.
l-prime of lambda.
Let's see Let's take the derivative of each
of these terms, the first term will give me
a minus n, the derivative as lambda, being
one.
The second term will give me the sum of x-i,
divided by lambda.
And here I'm just using the rule the derivative
of log lambda is one over lambda.
And the third term, you'll notice
is zero. There are no lambdas in this term.
And this is why we didn't trouble ourselves
seeing if we could more intelligently simplify
that term we were looking ahead, understanding
that only terms involving lambda would feature
in the computation of the log likelihood.
So that's the derivatives of the log likelihood.
I set this derivative equal to zero.
And as soon as I do, the parameter lambda
becomes lambda-hat. The particular value which
will maximize this log likelihood.
So then we solve for lambda-hat.
What do I get? I get the sum of x-i divided
by lambda-hat is equal to n.
Therefore, the maximum likelihood estimator,
lambda-hat is the sum of x-i over n.
That's also known as
the sample mean.