Hello everyone!
My name is Michelle Xia.
And I am an associate professor at Northern Illinois University.
In the previous lecture, we have learned the basic frequency distributions
for modeling claim counts.
In this lecture, I am going to introduce the (a, b, 0) class of distributions
and show that the Poisson, binomial, and negative binomial distributions
we learned in the previous lecture all belong to this class.
We first introduce the definition and properties of
the (a, b, 0) class of distributions.
For the definition, a count distribution is
a member of the (a, b, 0) class
if its probabilities pk satisfy the recursive formula that,
for any k from the support, the ratio of pk and p(k-1) equals
the sum of a constant "a" and a constant "b" divided by k.
Only three distributions are members of the (a, b, 0) class:
the Poisson distribution with the constant "a" equals 0,
the binomial distribution with "a" smaller than 0,
and the negative binomial distribution with "a" larger than 0.
For the (a, b, 0) class, the recursive expression given above
provides a computationally efficient way to generate the probabilities pk.
In addition, the recursive formulation allows us to
introduce modifications to the distributions.
In particular, in insurance, the treatment
of zero claims
often requires special adjustments
and the (a,b,0) structure allows us to readily accommodate these adjustments.
We will introduce such modifications later in Section 2.5.
For the three examples of (a, b, 0) frequency distributions,
we can obtain the corresponding recursive expressions
based on their probability mass functions, or pmfs.
For the first example, the Poisson distribution,
we recall that its probability pk has the
form
lambda of power k divided by k factorial times the exponential of negative lambda.
Plugging in the expressions of pk and p(k-1),
we can obtain their ratio as lambda divided by k.
Thus, the Poisson distribution belongs to the (a, b, 0) class
with "a" equals 0, "b" equals lambda
and the probability of "0", p0, equals
the exponential of negative lambda.
For the binomial distribution, we can show
that the constant "a" equals -q divided by (1-q),
"b" equals (m+1) times q divided by (1-q), and p0 equals (1-q) of power m.
Similarly, we can obtain the recursive expression
for the negative binomial distribution,
and verify that the constant "a" equals
beta divided by (1+beta),
"b" equals (r-1) times beta divided by (1+beta),
and p0 equals (1+beta) of power -r.
Using the above recursive formulas,
we can generate and modify the probabilities
for the three frequency distributions
when we know the parameter values.
In this section, you learn how to define
the (a, b, 0) class of frequency distributions
by deriving the recursive expressions
based on the probability mass functions.
We then discuss the importance of the recursive relationship
underpinning the (a, b, 0) class of frequency distributions.
Finally, we identify conditions under which
this general class reduces to each of
the binomial, Poisson,
and negative binomial distributions.
Based on the recursive expressions we derive
for the binomial, Poisson, and negative binomial distributions,
we can generate the probability mass functions
when we know the parameter values.
The exercise below shows how to generate Poisson
and negative binomial probabilities in R using the recursive formulas.