Hello everyone!
My name is Michelle Xia,
and I am an associate professor at Northern Illinois University.
In this lecture, I am going to introduce mixture distributions that are useful
for modeling frequency data from populations with multiple subgroups.
The first type of mixture distributions we introduce are discrete or finite mixtures.
For discrete mixtures, we suppose the population consists of several subgroups,
each having their own distribution referred to as the component distribution.
When we randomly draw an observation from the population
without knowing group membership,
the observation will follow a discrete mixture distribution.
We use auto insurance frequency data to illustrate the concept of discrete mixtures.
Suppose N1 represents the number of claims from good drivers (GD)
and N2 represents that from bad drivers (BD).
If N denotes the number of claims
of a randomly selected driver from the population,
N will follow a discrete mixture distribution.
Let alpha denote the percentage of good drivers.
Then there is a probability alpha that N will have the distribution of N1,
and a probability (1-alpha) that N will have the distribution of N2.
Here, alpha and (1-alpha) are called mixing proportions .
Here, we have a mixture of two subgroups.
But the mixture concept is applicable to cases with more than two groups.
Next, we will derive mixture probabilities for a 2-component mixture distribution.
The probability mass function (pmf) of a discrete mixture can be obtained
using the law of total probability from Probability Theory.
For the auto claims example, the probability that N takes any value k,
equals the joint probability that N equals k and the driver is a good driver
plus the joint probability that N equals k and the driver is a bad one.
Since the joint probability equals the product of the mixing proportion and the associated pmf,
the mixture pmf can be expressed as the weighted average of pmfs
with the weights alpha and (1-alpha).
Based on similar arguments, the cumulative distribution function (cdf)
of a discrete mixture can also be obtained as the weighted average
of the cdfs for the subgroups.
For populations with more than two subgroups,
similar expressions can be obtained for the mixture pmf and cdf.
We use an actuarial exam question to illustrate the calculation
for a 3-component mixture.
Assume that, in a certain town, the number of common colds
an individual will get in a year follows a Poisson distribution
depending on the individual's age and smoking status.
The table lists the three subgroups according to age and smoking status,
the population proportions,
and the mean numbers of colds for the Poisson components.
The question asks about the probability
that a randomly drawn person will have 3 common colds,
the pmf of the discrete mixture that can be expressed as the weighted average of Poisson component pmfs.
In addition, the question asks for the conditional probability that a person with exactly 3 common colds in a year is an adult smoker,
which can be obtained using the Bayes' rule from Probability.
Based on the definition, the moments of a discrete mixture can be expressed as a weighted average of its component moments.
We can first derive the mixture mean as a weighted average of the means of the subgroups
using the law of iterated expectations from Probability.
To extend the results to the second moment,
the expectation of N-squared, we simply write N-squared, N1-squared and N2-squared as random variables.
From the definition, N-squared will also have a discrete mixture distribution.
The same argument holds for any moment, defined as the expectation of N of power m.
The discrete mixtures we introduced are based on populations containing a finite number of subgroups.
We can extend the mixture idea to an infinite number of subgroups to obtain what we call continuous mixtures.
Consider we are interested in the distribution on the number of claims, N, among a population of drivers.
Assume the ith person from the population has their own Poisson distribution
with the expected number of claims, lambda i.
For some better drivers, lambda is small; for others, worse drivers, it is high.
We can assume that there is a distribution
for lambda, the Poisson mean.
In order to derive a closed-form for the continuous
mixture, a convenient distribution for lambda
is a gamma distribution with parameters alpha and theta.
One can check that if the number of claims, N, for the driver population follows a Poisson distribution
given its mean Lambda, and if the mean Lambda follows a gamma distribution
with parameters alpha and theta, then the marginal distribution of N is a negative binomial distribution
with parameters r equals alpha and beta equals theta.
Similar to discrete mixtures, we can derive the pmf and moments of continuous mixtures
when we know the pmfs and moments of the component distributions.
For the derivation, we consider a general framework with a random variable N from a continuous mixture,
and treat the population parameter Lambda as a random variable.
The first part gives the conditional pmf of N given Lambda = lambda.
Second, assume Lambda have a continuous pdf, or probability density function, f(lambda).
For a random draw N, we can obtain the marginal pmf pk using the following formula.
In the above derivation, we first determine the claim count pmf given a specific value lambda,
and then take the expectation over all possible values of lambda to get the claim count pmf for the random draw.
For obtaining the moments, we can use the law of iterated expectations to obtain raw moments,
and use the law of total variance to obtain the variance of N.
Technical details regarding the law of iterated expectations and the law of total variance
can be found in Section 16.1 of the Loss Data Analytics open text this lecture is based on.
Using the above framework, we can obtain the pmf and moments of the negative binomial distribution,
based on the Poisson-gamma mixture structure given in the previous slide.
In this section, you learned how to first define a mixture distribution
when the mixing component is based on a finite number
of subgroups;
then, compute mixture distribution probabilities from mixing proportions
and knowledge of the component distributions;
and last, define a mixture distribution when the mixing random variable is continuous.
From the definitions and examples, we note that any random draw from a population will have a mixture distribution,
when the population contains subgroups having different distributions.
Therefore, mixture distributions can be useful for insurance applications including frequency modeling.
If you are interested in more technical details regarding mixture distributions,
you may refer to Section 2.6 of the Loss Data Analytics open text.