Hello! I am Shyamal Kumar from the Department
of Statistics and Actuarial Science at the
University of Iowa. In this lecture, I will
talk on the goodness of fit problem.
We have discussed three basic frequency distributions,
along with their extensions through zero modification
and mixing. Nevertheless, such distributions
remain a small subset of the class of all
possible frequency distributions.
Hence, despite methods for efficiently estimating
the unknown parameters when the model is correct,
the fitted distribution need not be a good
representation of the underlying distribution
when the latter is far from the class of distributions
used for modeling. Determining if this is
the case is the goodness of fit problem.
Below we present one statistical test - based
on the Pearson's chi-square test statistic
- to check for the appropriateness of the
fitted distribution as a model for the observed
data. We do so through an example based on
Singaporean auto insurance data.
In 1993, a portfolio of 7,483 auto insurance
policies from a major Singaporean insurance
company had the distribution of accidents
per policy as given in the displayed table.
The observed maximum number of accidents per
policy was three, and on average, there were
about 70 accidents per 1,000 policies.
Consider an actuary who is evaluating the
Poisson model for this data.
The first step would be to fit the Poisson
model to this data, and for this, one can
employ the maximum likelihood method for estimating
the Poisson mean. Doing so would result in
the fitted Poisson mean equal to the sample
mean of about 0.069.
Next, one would partition the non-negative
integers into cells or bins such that the
expected number of counts in at least 80%
of the cells, for the sample size of 7,483,
is above 5.
In our case, it is natural to have four singleton
cells for counts 0, 1, 2, and 3 and a cell
for counts greater than 3. The table displayed
gives for each cell the observed and fitted
counts derived using the fitted Poisson.
It is natural to ask, is the Poisson model
a good fit?
To evaluate the fit, we will use the shown
Pearson's chi-square statistic. Chi-square
refers to its limiting distribution if the
Poisson model is correct. Its degrees of freedom
equals the number of cells minus one minus
the number of estimated parameters. In our
example, we estimated one parameter, lambda,
and have five cells, and hence the degrees
of freedom equals three.
For the data given the Pearson's chi-square
statistic equals about 42, while even the
99th percentile of chi-square with three degrees
of freedom is below 12. Hence, we deem the
Poisson model to be an inadequate representation
of the underlying data.
In the exercise below, you would evaluate
the adequacy instead of the larger zero-modified
Poisson model.
Thank you!