Hello! I am Shyamal Kumar from the Department
of Statistics and Actuarial Science
at the University of Iowa. This lecture concerns
maximum likelihood estimation for the binomial
and the negative binomial models.
Many experiments generate random outcomes
that are binomial or near binomial.
For such experiments, the parameter
m is self-evident. For this reason,
the binomial model is a single parameter
model in introductory statistics courses.
In actuarial frequency modeling,
lacking such an underlying experiment,
the binomial as a two-parameter model with
the parameter m unknown is more effective.
The log-likelihood shown here is a smooth function
of q for a fixed value of m. For a given value of
m, maximizing the log-likelihood with respect
to q alone yields that the maximizing value of q
satisfies q times m equals the sample mean.
The MLE for the parameter m is then seen to
be the arg max of the reduced log-likelihood
with q set equal to the sample mean over m.
This maximization can be restricted to values of
m at least the sample maximum as
otherwise, the likelihood equals zero.
Also, since the parameter m is a natural number,
brute-force maximization is quite effective.
A cautionary note is that, unlike
typical models, the MLE need not
exist. The latter happens precisely when the
sample variance is at least the sample mean,
in which case the data is
suggestive of the Poisson model.
The sum of n independent geometric random
variables is a negative binomial random variable
with the parameter r equal to n, a natural number.
For this reason, in statistical texts, the
negative binomial model is often reduced
by restricting r to be a natural number. Since
this interpretation of a negative binomial is
not relevant in frequency modeling, r is
allowed to take any positive real value.
The log-likelihood shown here
is a smooth function of beta
for a fixed value of r. For a given value of r,
maximizing the log-likelihood with respect to beta
alone yields that the maximizing value of beta
satisfies beta times r equals the sample mean.
The MLE for the parameter r is
then seen to be the arg max of the
reduced log-likelihood with beta set
equal to the sample mean over r.
Hence, computing the MLE is a problem of
optimizing a smooth function of one real variable,
and commonly available numerical routines can be
effectively employed. For optimization algorithms
requesting an approximate solution,
the moment estimator for r can be used.
Again, a cautionary note is
that, unlike typical models,
the MLE need not exist. The latter happens when
the sample variance is at most the sample mean,
in which case the data is
suggestive of the Poisson model.
It may have piqued your curiosity
about why the MLE does not exist
for some samples when using the binomial
and the negative binomial models.
The underlying reason is that
any given Poisson distribution
is a limit of a sequence of binomials
and a sequence of negative binomials,
while no Poisson is either a binomial or a
negative binomial. Poisson limit is attained when
m approaches infinity for binomials, and their
common mean equals that of the Poisson limit.
And in the case of the negative
binomials, they approach a Poisson
when r grows to infinity, and their common
mean equals that of the Poisson limit.
The above observation makes the optimization
related to the MLE akin to maximizing
a strictly increasing function on an open
interval. For example, the function h(x)=x^2
on the open interval (0,1) does not attain a
maximum, though it gets arbitrarily close to 1.
In the following two exercises, you will solve the
optimization problems underlying the MLE method
for the binomial and the negative
binomial in the R software environment.
Thank you!