Hello everyone!
My name is Michelle Xia, and I am an associate
professor at Northern Illinois University.
In this lecture, I am going to introduce
the basic frequency distributions
for modeling claim counts.
For frequency distributions, the term frequency
refers to how often an insured event occurs,
typically within a policy contract, for example,
one year for short-term insurance.
Frequency modeling is often
conducted in the contexts of
ratemaking, stochastic
reserving and claims analytics.
In practice, discrete probability distributions,
called count distributions, are used to
model the number of losses to a policyholder
or the number of claims to an insurance company.
For basic frequency distributions, we first
introduce the probability foundations.
In order to define count distributions, we
focus on the frequency random variable N
with support on k = 0, 1, 2, up to infinity.
That is, the random variable
on the number of losses
in the insurance context,
can take any whole number.
Given the support, the frequency distribution
is characterized by the probability mass function,
pmf, the probability that the random variable
takes each value k from its support.
We use lower-case pk to denote the pmf.
Alternatively, we can use the
cumulative distribution function,
cdf, to uniquely determine
the probability distribution
of a count random variable.
The cdf is defined as the probability that
N takes a value no larger than x on the real line.
The cdf F(x) can be calculated
as the sum of the pmfs associated with
all whole numbers no larger than x.
Furthermore, we can summarize distributions
through moments.
The most commonly seen moment, the mean,
measures the center of the count distribution.
The mean E(N), also denoted mu,
is the expectation of the random variable N,
and can be calculated as
the sum of all possible values of k
multiplied by its associated probability pk.
Another commonly seen moment, variance,
measures the variability of the random variable N.
In particular, the variance Var(N) is defined
as the expectation of the squared difference
between N and its mean mu, and can be
calculated as the difference between the
expectation of N-squared and mu-squared.
Other than the probability distribution functions
introduced in the previous slide,
the distribution of a random
variable can be determined
using probability generating functions.
The probability generating function, pgf,
can uniquely determine the
distribution of a random variable.
The pgf, denoted capital P of some z,
is defined as the expectation of z of power N,
and can be calculated as a weighted average of
z of power k with the weights being the pmfs.
The name probability generating function comes
from the property that, taking the mth derivative
and evaluating the function at 0, pgf generates
probabilities multiplied by m factorial.
Further, pgf can generate moments.
For example, taking the first derivative and
evaluating the function at 1 gives the mean E(N),
and taking the second derivative
and evaluating the function at 1 gives
the expectation of N times N-1,
which allows us to obtain the variance.
After introducing the probability foundations,
we can now define important
frequency distributions
commonly seen in the actuarial context.
In particular, there are three important frequency
distributions, including
the Poisson, binomial and negative
binomial distributions that
we will introduce in this lecture.
The three distributions are important
because they fit well many
insurance data sets of interest,
and they provide the basis for more
complex distributions that even
better approximate real situations of interest.
In what follows, we will define these
three frequency distributions
based on the probability theories
introduced earlier.
The first important distribution we introduce
is the Poisson distribution
that is commonly used to
model count random variables
on the number of claims.
The Poisson distribution
is a parametric distribution
that has a positive parameter lambda,
with its pmf pk given as follows.
The Poisson distribution
does not have a closed-form for its cdf
but it can be numerically evaluated
given specific values of lambda.
And its pgf capital P of z has the form
exponential lambda times z-1.
The expectation of the Poisson
distribution is lambda,
which is the same as the variance.
The second important frequency distribution,
the binomial distribution, is commonly used
to model the number of successes
from a fixed number of binary trials.
Thus, the binomial distribution
has two parameters:
m on the number of trials
that is known from the design,
and a parameter q on the probability
of success, between 0 and 1.
The binomial pmf and pgf have the following forms.
Based on the design of a binomial trial,
the support of a binomial distribution contains
the values 0, 1, up to m.
The binomial mean is m times q,
and the variance is m times q times 1-q.
If the number of trials, m, equals 1, the
distribution is called a Bernoulli distribution.
Here, as the probability q is between 0 and 1,
the variance is always smaller than the mean
for binomial distributions.
The third important frequency distribution
used for modeling claim counts
is the negative binomial distribution.
The negative binomial distribution has
two positive parameters, r and beta,
and it models the number of successes
occurring before the rth failure.
Here, beta divided by beta plus 1
denotes the probability of success,
and the negative binomial pmf and pgf
have the following forms.
The negative binomial distribution has
the expectation r times beta,
and variance r times beta times 1 plus beta.
If the parameter r equals 1, then
it is called a geometric distribution.
Since beta is positive,
the negative binomial distribution
has the property that
the variance is larger than the mean.
It is useful for modeling
over-dispersed count data,
where the empirical variance
is larger than the empirical mean.
In this lecture, we have
learned the definitions and properties
of basic frequency distributions
actuaries use to model the number of losses.
We first determine quantities that summarize
a distribution such as the probability and
distribution functions, as well as moments
such as the mean and variance.
We then define and compute the moment and
probability generating functions.
Last, we describe and understand relationships
among three important frequency distributions,
the binomial, Poisson, and negative binomial
distributions that are commonly used
for loss frequency data on the number of claims.