11:24:12 Alright, so here we're going to expand
on one of the videos from the textbook and
use it to explore a little bit more What a
Bayesian prior distribution is, what a posterior
distribution is, and what a predictive distribution
is.
11:24:32 So getting right to it.
11:24:34 We're going to look at example 4.4.5.
11:24:39 This is an actuarial exam question.
And here's what we're given. The probability
that an insured has at least one loss in any
given year is p. So that's our parameter.
11:24:52 This is a Bayesian and problem. So
we're going to focus on the prior distribution
for that one parameter, and we're told it's
uniform between zero and point five.
11:25:06 But for one particular customer,
they've had eight consecutive years of at
least one loss.
11:25:14 And we're asked to calculate the
posterior probability that that person will
again have another loss in year nine.
11:25:23 Okay, so just thinking about it it
seems like this particular customer has a
much higher probability of giving losses we've
seen eight in a row, we might really guess
that they're likely to have a ninth one, and
this is a classic example of the power of
11:25:39 Bayesian methods.
11:25:41 So we'll start with a little bit
of notation. I'm going to call X-i equal one
11:25:49 if the customer had at least one
loss
11:25:58 in year i.
11:26:02 And of course this parameter p sitting
right here is understood as the probability
that x-i is equal to one.
11:26:13 Okay, so that's the setup.
11:26:14 What are they asking me for.
11:26:16 They're asking for the posterior
probability that this person will have a loss
in year nine.
11:26:25 The probability that x-nine is equal
to one, given
11:26:33 they've had a loss, every year for
eight years.
11:26:37 Okay.
11:26:38 Given that they had a loss in year
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, all the way through 8.
11:26:48 This is what I'm being asked to find.
11:26:52 And this is the posterior predictive
distribution.
11:27:04 Why is that the posterior predictive
distribution? Well let's take a look at it.
11:27:10 All of this information right here,
x-one through x-eight.
11:27:15 This is past data. Given I have observed
that.
11:27:23 What can I say about future?
11:27:29 What can I say about another unobserved
random variable?
11:27:35 Okay, so I take what I know about
the past and I'm somehow supposed to use that
to better inform a future prediction.
11:27:44 And as the textbook shows the definition
of this thing of course is the probability
X-nine is equal to one, given.
11:27:54 I know the parameter p
11:27:58 times the probability of p given
I know,
11:28:06 eight years of loss data.
11:28:09 And I integrate over the parameter
p.
11:28:19 This is the definition of the predictive
distribution.
11:28:25 And notice, in particular, we have
sitting right here, the posterior distribution.
11:28:34 This is my updated information about
the parameter p, given I have observed eight
years of data.
11:28:46 So let's collect what we know so
far, we have a prior distribution, which was
given to us in the problem --- uniform between
0 and 0.5
11:29:00 prior is pi p, which is uniform between
0 and 0.5.
11:29:09 I'm going to draw the prior over
here. Here's my parameter p start at zero.
11:29:19 This thing is founded at 0.5.
11:29:21 And of course if it's uniform.
11:29:24 What that means, let's see what color
should I use for the prior prior will henceforth
be red.
11:29:33 It is every value equally likely.
11:29:38 That's the prior.
11:29:43 Well then I have a customer with
eight years of consecutive losses. So I need
to compute the posterior.
11:29:55 This is pi of p given x-1 is a loss,
all the way through x-8 is a loss.
11:30:05 Okay, so we use what we know about
Bayesian methods in general, this posterior
of course is going to be proportional to the
probability year one was a loss, given p times
year 2, 3, 4,5,6,7,8 was a loss...
11:30:27 times the prior.
11:30:34 And, of course, this is p times ... times
p. There are eight of them, times the prior,
which is 2... the posterior will be proportional
to p to the eighth power.
11:30:53 And in the textbook, it goes through
how to find the normalizing constant, because
we know that the posterior is a density and
must integrate to one.
11:31:03 So in fact, the posterior
11:31:09 is equal to nine times 0.5 to the
negative ninth power times p to the eighth.
11:31:22 Alright, let's take a look at that
here.
11:31:25 This by the way, is the posterior.
11:31:29 This is what I'm going to plug in
for the predictive density.
11:31:36 And if this is proportional to p
to the eighth, when p is small, near zero,
this is going to be very small.
11:31:45 And when p is larger, this is going
to be larger the posterior looks something
like this.
11:32:00 And that makes sense, because this
person, after all, has had eight consecutive
years of losses.
11:32:10 So probably for this person they
have a much larger probability of experiencing
a loss, they just seem to be a riskier customer.
11:32:20 And so we have finally set the table
for solving the problem that we need to solve.
11:32:26 We want to ask ourselves what is
the probability that this person, after eight
years of losses, will experience at least
one more loss next year.
11:32:37 All we need to do now that we have
our posterior is integrate the probability
of one more loss given p times the posterior
dp, we need to evaluate this predictive distribution.
11:32:52 So doing that, of course, the probability
next year is at least the loss
11:32:59 Given the last eight is the integral.
11:33:11 0 to 0.5...
11:33:08 the probability of one more loss...
11:33:10 Given p times the posterior
11:33:16 dp. The probability of one more loss
--- that's just p ---
11:33:26 The posterior is nine times point
five to the negative ninth power times p to
the eight.
11:33:36 And I integrate this over p.
11:33:40 So we can move some constants out
front. I get a nine times 0.5 to the negative
ninth power.
11:33:48 I have a p to the nine, and I integrate
that, so of course I get one over 10 times
p to the 10th power.
11:33:58 And I evaluate this expression between
0.5 and 0.
11:34:05 So we collect some terms I'll get
the nine out front. Bring the 10 over.
11:34:11 Of course I have point five to the
negative nine, and that's going to be multiplied
by point five to the 10. So only a point five
remains.
11:34:20 Then when I plug in zero, the whole
expression is equal to zero.
11:34:24 So this is point five times nine
over 10, which is equal to 0.45.
11:34:36 And let's think about that number
in the context of the problem. We've already
established this was a very risky customer,
they've had eight consecutive years of losses.
11:34:47 Even though my prior distribution
thought the probability someone would get
a loss was evenly distributed between zero
and 0.5.
11:34:56 For this risky customer after eight
years of losses. I'm pretty sure their probability
of a loss is much higher.