Hello, my name is Fei Huang, a senior
lecturer at the UNSW Sydney.
In this video, we will review Section 3.2
Continuous Distributions for
modelling Loss Severity.
In particular, we learn how to define and
apply four fundamental severity distributions:
gamma, Pareto, Weibull, and generalized
beta distribution of the second kind.
The first distribution is the gamma distribution.
The probability density of a gamma distribution
with shape parameter \alpha and scale parameter
\theta is defined by this formula in this slide.
When \alpha=1, the gamma reduces to an exponential
distribution. When \alpha=n/2 and \theta=2,
the gamma reduces to a chi-square distribution
with n degrees of freedom. As we will see in
Section 15.4, the chi-square distribution is used
extensively in statistical hypothesis testing.
In this slide, we use the two plots to demonstrate
the effect of the scale and shape parameters on
the gamma density function. In the left-hand
panel, we see the gamma density plots with
shape=2 and varying scale parameter. While in the
right-hand panel, we see the Pareto Density plots
with scale=100 and varying shape parameter.
The distribution function of a gamma model is the
incomplete gamma function and defined
in the formula in this slide.
We can also define the k-th raw moment, mean,
and variance of the gamma distributed random
variable for any positive k. For example, the
mean is \alpha times \theta and the variance is
\alpha times \theta^2. Since all moments exist
for any positive k, the gamma distribution is
considered a light tailed distribution, which
may not be suitable for modelling risky assets
as it will not provide a realistic assessment
of the likelihood of severe losses.
Another important feature of
the gamma distribution is that
it belongs to the exponential family of
distributions. This means that it is easy
to incorporate explanatory variables into the
distribution via generalized linear modelling.
Next, we introduce the Pareto distribution. It is
a positively skewed and heavy-tailed distribution
which makes it suitable for modelling income,
high-risk insurance claims and severity of large
casualty losses. For extreme insurance claims, the
tail of the severity distribution can be modelled
using a generalized Pareto distribution. For
example, in my own research of modelling advanced
age mortality, I used the generalized Pareto
distribution to model mortality over a specific
age threshold. The probability density
function of a two parameter Pareto distribution
with shape parameter \alpha and scale
parameter \theta is given in this slide.
In this slide, we use the two plots
to demonstrate the effect of the scale
and shape parameters on the Pareto density
function. In the left-hand panel, we see the
Pareto Density plots with scale 2000 and varying
shape parameter. While in the right-hand panel,
we see the Pareto Density plots with
shape 3 and varying scale parameter.
In this slide, we show the distribution function
of the Pareto distribution, the k-th raw moment,
the mean and variance of the Pareto
distributed random variable.
The third distribution we introduce
here is called the Weibull distribution.
The probability density function of the Weibull
distribution is given by this formula with shape
parameter \alpha and scale parameter \theta. We
can also calculate the hazard function of the
Weibull distribution, which is the probability
density function over the survival function.
The hazard function is a decreasing function when
\alpha<1, indicating heavy tailed distribution.
It is constant when \alpha=1 and increasing when
\alpha >1, indicating light tailed distribution.
We also show the distribution
function of the Weibull distribution
given at the bottom of the slide.
In this slide, we derive the k-th raw moment,
the mean and variance of the Weibull
distributed random variable.
The fourth distribution we introduce is the
generalized Beta distribution of the second
kind, denoted by GB2 distribution. It is a
four-parameter, very flexible distribution
that can model positively as well as negatively
skewed distributions. We show the probability
density function of the GB2 distribution and
the beta function via the formulas there.
The GB2 distribution can provide a model
for heavy as well as light tailed data. It
includes many distributions as special cases,
such as exponential, gamma, Weibull, etc.
For example, suppose we have 2 independent Gamma
distributed random variables G1 and G2. Then
the random variable \theta times (G1/G2)^\sigma
has a GB2 distribution. When the moment exists,
we can also compute the k-th raw moment
using the bottom formula in this slide.
In Exercise 3.2.1, we will be working
with the Wisconsin Property Fund data.
We have read the data and created a vector
of the log of non-zero claim values.
You will be asked to plot a histogram of the
data using the hist function in R and use the
`str` function to review the elements of the
list returned by the histogram function.
In Exercise 3.2.2, we will focus on the
gamma distribution from Section 3.2.1
to help you develop an intuition as
to how the distribution responds to
changes in its shape and scale parameter.
From Figure 3.1, you should recognize that
the support for the gamma distribution is
positive real numbers. You ll also note that
the distribution allows for varying levels
of right-skewness. You can use the `hist`
function to plot a histogram of the data, use
the `dgamma` function to return density values,
and use the curve` function to plot the
gamma distribution over the histogram data.
Please be careful in setting the arguments of
each function. In this exercise, you will also
have the chance to calculate shape and scale
parameters using the method of moments.
Packages in R exist for most
continuous distributions,
however, it is useful to be able to
know how to write your own functions.
In R, a function is an object so the R interpreter
is able to pass control to the function,
along with arguments that may be necessary for
the function to accomplish the actions. Functions
allow you to automate common tasks in a more
powerful and general way than copy-and-pasting.
In Exercise 3.2.3, we will write an R function to
find the density (the pdf) of a random variable
that follows a Pareto distribution.
In summary, in this section,
we learnt how to define and apply four
fundamental severity distributions,
including gamma, Pareto, Weibull, and generalized
beta distribution of the second kind.