Hello, welcome back to this video on introduction
to Loss Data Analytics
My name is Nii Okine; I am an assistant professor
at the Maths Department of Appalachian State
University.
In this video, we are going to continue our
discussion on the impacts of coverage modifications
with a focus on coinsurance, and reinsurance.
Under a coinsurance policy, the retained loss
by the insurer is a percentage of the incurred
loss X.
The percentage ?, often referred to as the
coinsurance factor, is the percentage of claim
the insurance company is required to cover.
If the policy is subject to an ordinary deductible
and policy limit, coinsurance refers to the
percentage of claim the insurer is required
to cover, after imposing the ordinary deductible
d and policy limit u.
Then, the payment per loss variable, YL, is
equal to zero for values of X that are less
than or equal to d, equal to alpha multiplied
by X-d for values of X that are greater than
d but less than of equal to u, and equal to
alpha multiplied by u-d for values of X greater
than u.
The maximum amount paid by the insurer in
this case is ?(u?d), while u is the maximum
covered loss.
When a loss is subject to both a deductible
d and a limit u the per-loss variable YL can
be expressed as the limited loss variable
at the limit u minus the limited loss variable
at the limit d. With coinsurance, the payment
per loss random variable YL can be expressed
as alpha multiplied by the limited loss variable
at the limit u minus the limited loss variable
at the limit d.
Then the expected value of the payment per
loss variable equal to the alpha multiplied
by the limited expected value at u minus the
limited expected value at d.
The k-th moment of the payment per loss random
variable is expressed using the initial definition
of payment per loss variable and given as
shown.
A growth factor (1+r) may be applied to X
resulting in an inflated loss random variable
(1+r)X
With the prespecified d and u remain unchanged,
the resulting per loss variable can be written
as equal to zero for values of X that are
less than or equal to d divided by 1+r, equal
to alpha multiplied by (1+r)X-d for values
of X that are greater than d divided by 1+r
but less than or equal to u divided by 1+r,
and equal to alpha multiplied by u-d for values
of X greater than u divided by 1+r.
Note that the limit and deductible are divided
by 1+r to correspond to the deflated values.
The first moment of the payment per loss variable
equal to the alpha multiplied by 1+r multiplied
by the limited expected value at u divided
by 1+r minus the limited expected value at
d divided by 1+r. In this case we have the
maximum covered loss and the deductible at
their deflated values, computed the average
payment, and then reinflated back.
For the second moments, we can incorporate
inflation in a manner similar to the formulas
for first moments. However, since the second
moment is in dollars squared,
we reinflate back by multiplying by (1+r)
squared. Also, we multiply by the coinsurance
factor squared. Then the second moment can
be expressed as shown.
One can combine the formulas for the first
and second moments in order to calculate the
variance.
The formulas given for the first and second
moments of YL are general. Under full coverage,
?=1, r=0, u=?, d=0 and expected value of YL
reduces to expected of X.
If only an ordinary deductible is imposed,
?=1, r=0, u=? and expected value of YL reduces
to expected of X minus limited expected value
at d.
If only a policy limit is imposed ?=1, r=0,
d=0 and expected value of YL reduces to limited
expected value at u.
We now consider an actuarial exam question.
We have been given that the ground up loss
random variable for a health insurance policy
in 2006 is modeled with X, a random variable
with an exponential distribution having mean
1000. An insurance policy pays the loss above
an ordinary deductible of 100, with a maximum
annual payment of 500. The ground up loss
random variable is expected to be 5% larger
in 2007, but the insurance in 2007 has the
same deductible and maximum payment as in
2006. Find the percentage increase in the
expected cost per payment from 2006 to 2007.
To answer this question, first, we need to
define the amount per loss variable YL for
2006, and 2007.
The amount per loss variable YL for 2006 is
equal to zero for values of X that are less
than or equal to 100, equal to X-100 for values
of X that are greater than 100 but less than
or equal to 600, and equal to 500, that is
600 minus 100 for values of X greater than
600.
Also, with inflation rate equal to 5%, the
amount per loss variable YL for 2007 is equal
to zero for values of X that are less than
or equal to 100 divided by 1.05 that is 95.24,
equal to 1.05X-100 for values of X that are
greater than 95.24 but less than or equal
to 571.43 which is 600 divided by 1.05, and
YL is equal to 500 that is 600 minus 100 for
values of X greater than 571.43.
The expected cost per payment from 2006 is
equal to the expected cost per loss from 2006
divided by survival of X at the deductible
100. Solving using the limited loss random
variable and survival function based on the
exponential distribution gives us an answer
of 393.469.
Similarly, solving for the expected cost per
payment from 2007 gives us an answer of 397.797.
Then, the percentage increase in the expected
cost per payment from 2006 to 2007 is given
by the expected cost per payment from 2007
divided by the expected cost per payment from
2006 minus 1. Which is equal to 1.1%
Therefore, there is an increase of 1.1% from
2006 to 2007. Due to the policy limit, the
cost per payment event grew by only 1.1% between
2006 and 2007 even though the ground up losses
increased by 5% between the two years.
Here, we discuss an example of R code that
we can use to calculate the expected value
of the claims insured subject to a deductible
and a policy limit.
The first chunk of code assigns the parameters
for the lognormal distribution and simulates
the claims severities.
The second chunk of code determines the number
of claims resulting in reimbursement both
from the data and based on the lognormal model
using plnorm, the distribution function of
the lognormal model.
The third chunk of code calculates the expected
value of the claims insured subject to a $1
million deductible and a $5 million policy
limit.
The last chunk of code calculates the expected
value of the claims insured subject to a $1
million deductible and a $5 million policy
limit based on the lognormal distribution
using the levlnorm function, a user-defined
function introduced in the previous video.
The tutorial you will be working on at the
end of this video will require you to calculates
the expected values of claims under a policy
with a deductible, policy limit, and coinsurance.
In a
deductible policy insurance contract, there
is a contractual arrangement under which an
insured transfers part of the risk by securing
coverage from an insurer in return for an
insurance premium. Under that policy, the
insured must pay all losses up to the deductible,
and the insurer only pays the amount (if any)
above the deductible.
Under the reinsurance, there is a contractual
arrangement under which an insurer transfers
part of the underlying insured risk by securing
coverage from another insurer referred to
as a reinsurer in return for a reinsurance
premium.
Although reinsurance involves a relationship
between three parties: the original insured,
the insurer often referred to as cedant and
the reinsurer, the parties of the reinsurance
agreement are only the primary insurer and
the reinsurer. There is no contractual agreement
between the original insured and the reinsurer.
Though many different types of reinsurance
contracts exist, a common form is the excess
of loss coverage. In such contracts, the primary
insurer must make all required payments to
the insured until the primary insurer s total
payments reach a fixed reinsurance deducible.
The reinsurer is then only responsible for
paying losses above the reinsurance deductible.
The maximum amount retained by the primary
insurer in the reinsurance agreement is called
retention.
Reinsurance arrangements allow insurers with
limited financial resources to increase the
capacity to write insurance and meet client
requests for larger insurance coverage while
reducing the impact of potential losses and
protecting the insurance company against catastrophic
losses.
Reinsurance also allows the primary insurer
to benefit from underwriting skills, expertise
and proficient complex claim file handling
of the larger reinsurance companies.
This is the last video in a series of three
videos in this section. We introduced standard
mechanisms that insurers use to reduce or
mitigate their risk, including deductibles,
policy limits, and coinsurance.
In this video, we evaluated the impacts of
coinsurance and inflation on insurer's costs.
And we examined how the distribution of the
insurer's obligations depends on these mechanisms.
We also introduced reinsurance, a mechanism
of insurance for insurance companies, and
discussed the advantages of reinsurance to
the primary insurer.
Thank you for watching this video.