Hello, welcome back to this video on introduction
to Loss Data Analytics
My name is Nii Okine; I am an assistant professor
at the Maths Department of Appalachian State
University.
In this video, I am going to discuss different
methods of creating new distributions.
In the previous sections of this chapter,
we discussed some important and commonly known
continuous distributions.
Some of the continuous distributions discussed
are gamma, Pareto, Weibull, and generalized
beta distribution of the second kind or GB2
distribution.
Continuous distributions are used to model
continuous variables, for example, the claim
sizes or amount.
In this section, we will be discussing two
main approaches to creating new distributions.
The first approach, which will be covered
in this video, concerns creating new distributions
by transforming the random variable of a distribution.
Under this approach, we will look at three
transformation techniques for creating new
distributions, that is, multiplying by a constant,
raising to a power, and exponentiation.
In the following slides, we will discuss these
common techniques in detail.
The second approach, which will be covered
in the next video, deals with creating a new
distribution by combining other distributions.
Two common techniques to combine distributions
under the second approach are Mixing and Splicing.
We first consider creating new distributions
by multiplying a random variable by a positive
constant.
In insurance, such transformations can be
useful to adjust for the change in claim data
over time due to inflation. To adjust for
inflation, we multiply the losses X by 1+inflation
rate. For example, if the inflation rate is
8%, we can create a new variable Y=1.08X.
We can also use such transformations to convert
a loss random variable X in dollars to thousands
of dollars. Such that the new variable Y=1/1000X.
Another application of such transformations
is to convert losses to different currencies
by multiplying the random variable X by the
exchange rate.
In general, the new variable is given by Y=cX,
Because the distribution function of the random
variable X is known, it can be shown that
the distribution function of Y is given by
the cdf of X evaluated at y/c.
Using the chain rule for differentiation,
we can obtain the pdf of the new variable
Y as 1/c times the pdf of X at y/c.
In a scale distribution, the new variable
Y=cX is in the same set of distributions as
the random variable X.
In general, when a member of a scale distribution
is multiplied by a constant c, the scale parameter
meets two conditions:
1. The parameter is changed by multiplying
by c;
2. All other parameters remain unchanged.
Many loss distributions are scale distributions.
For example, Gamma distribution.
The next transformation technique we take
a look at is Raising to a power. This technique
involves raising the random variable to a
power.
Looking at the Weibull distribution origins,
we recognize that the Weibull is a Power transformation
of the exponential distribution. We will return
to this relationship between the exponential
and Weibull distribution in the next couple
of slides.
Under the Raising to a Power technique, the
new variable Y is defined by Y=X raise to
the power tau.
We examine three cases of tau.
The first case is when tau> 0. In this case,
it can be shown that the cdf of the new variable
Y is given by the cdf of X evaluated at y
raised to the power one divided by tau.
We then use the chain rule for differentiation
to obtain the pdf.
On the other hand, when tau< 0. It can be
shown that the cdf of the new variable Y is
given by one minus the cdf of X evaluated
at y raised to the power one divided by tau.
Again, to obtain the pdf of the new variable
Y, we apply the chain rule of differentiation.
For the third case, we consider tau=-1. Then,
the new variable Y is the inverse of X. The
cdf and pdf of Y is a special case of the
case when tau< 0.
Here is an example of transforming an exponential
distribution to an inverse exponential distribution
using the inverse transformation.
Suppose that X has an exponential distribution
with parameter theta star, then an inverse
transformation will give us Y=1/X.
The distribution function of Y is given by
exp raise to the negative one divided by the
product of y and theta star.
If we define a new parameter theta= 1/theta
star, then the resulting distribution function
is that of an inverse exponential function
with parameter theta.
We can also transform an Exponential distribution
into a Weibull distribution.
Here, we start with a variable X which follows
an exponential distribution with parameter
1.
Then we can define a new random variable of
the form: Y=theta multiplied by X to the power
1 divided by tau.
Here theta and tau are positive parameters.
Then we can show that the cdf of Y is that
of the Weibull function with parameters theta
and tau.
Another type of transformation involves exponentiating
a random variable X so that the new variable
Y is defined by Y= e to the power X.
Then the cdf of Y is given by the cdf of X
evaluated at the natural log of y
And we obtain the pdf by the chain rule.
The normal distribution is a very popular
model for a wide number of applications. If
a random variable X has a normal distribution,
then Y= e to the power X follows a lognormal
distribution.
The lognormal distribution is positively skewed
with a long right tail and is commonly used
to describe financial assets such as stock
prices.
Also, the natural log transformation is another
transformation that is commonly used in actuarial
practice. When the new variable Y is equal
to the natural log of X, then the cdf of Y
is given by the distribution function of X
evaluated at e to the power y. When we use
the chain rule, the pdf of Y is given by x
multiplied by the pdf of X at x.
Here we discuss an example of R code that
we can use to obtain the pdf of a log transformed
variable Y and create a plot.
For this example, we assume a Gamma distribution,
so the first two lines assign values for the
shape parameter alpha and scale parameter
theta.
The next line assigns values to X, representing
the claim severities. We then use the dgamma
function in R to generate a pdf of the claim
severities, assuming the Gamma distribution
with the above parameters.
The next chunk of codes transforms the x variable
using natural logarithms to obtain y. Then
the pdf of Y is given by x multiplied by the
pdf of X at x. The last line of code plots
the pdf curve of the log claim severity.
In this video, we provided foundations for
creating new distributions. Specifically,
we looked at an approach that deals with transforming
a random variable of a distribution. We discussed
techniques such as multiplication by a constant,
raising to a power, and exponentiation.
We also provided connections among distributions.
For example, we discussed the connection between
the exponential and inverse exponential functions
and also the exponential and Weibull functions.
Thank you for watching this video.