Hello, welcome back to this video on introduction
to Loss Data Analytics
My name is Nii Okine; I am an assistant professor
at the Maths Department of Appalachian State
University.
In this video, we are going to continue our
discussion on different methods of creating
new distributions.
In this section, we introduce two main approaches
to creating new distributions.
In the previous video, we discussed an approach
that concerns creating new distributions by
transforming the random variable of a distribution.
We looked at three transformation techniques
for creating new distributions, i.e., multiplying
by a constant, raising to a power, and exponentiating.
This video will discuss the second approach,
which deals with creating a new distribution
by combining other distributions. Two common
techniques we are going to discuss are Mixing
and Splicing.
In the following slides, we will discuss these
common techniques in detail.
We begin with a technique called Mixing. Mixing
distributions represent a useful way of modeling
data that are drawn from a heterogeneous parent
population.
This parent population can be thought to be
divided into multiple homogenous subpopulations
with distinct distributions.
Suppose the underlying phenomenon is diverse
and can be described as k phenomena representing
k subpopulations with different modes. In
that case, we can construct a k-point mixture
random variable Y.
Let random variables X1 to Xk represent the
subpopulations, then Y is defined as piecewise
function of the X1, to Xk random variables
where the alphas are the mixing parameters
representing the proportion of data points
that fall under each of the subpopulations.
We have to note that the sum of the alpha
must add up to one.
The distribution function of Y is given as
the weighted average of the components distribution
functions. The same applies to the pdfs.
This weighted average can be applied to many
other distribution-related quantities, such
as the k-th raw moment.
Therefore the mean of Y is the weighted average
of the component means.
We now consider an actuarial exam question.
We have been given that a collection of insurance
policies consists of two types. 25% of policies
are Type 1 and 75% of policies are Type 2.
For a policy of Type 1, the loss amount per
year follows an exponential distribution with
mean 200, and for a policy of Type 2, the
loss amount per year follows a Pareto distribution
with parameters alpha=3 and theta=200.
We are asked to calculate the probability
that the annual loss will be less than 100,
and also find the average loss.
To answer this question, first, we need to
recall that for the two-point mixture variable
X, to find the probability that X less than
100, we need to use the weighted average of
the components distribution functions.
For the exponential distribution, the distribution
function is given by 1- e to the power negative
x divided by theta. Given theta equals 200
and x equals 100, solving gives us the cdf
of X1 at 100 to be 0.393.
For the pareto distribution the distribution
function is given by 1- (theta/(theta +x))^alpha.
With alpha equals 3, theta equals 200, and
x equals 100, solving gives us the cdf of
X2 at 100 to be 0.704.
Finally, substituting the distribution functions
into the weighted average equation and solving,
we get the cdf at 100 to be 0.626
Further, the average loss is given by the
weighted average of the component means. Solving
gives us an average loss to be 125.
Now we discuss an example of R code that we
can use to generate a mixture distribution.
For this example, we assume the claim severities
for each subpopulation are expected to follow
Gamma distributions with different shape parameters
alpha and different scale parameters theta.
This R code combines the Gamma probability
density functions together to produce a mixture
distribution, plot the pdfs for the log of
the claim severities for each subpopulation,
and the mixture distribution.
The first chunk of codes creates a vector
of alphas and thetas for the two subpopulations
and plot the pdfs for each subpopulation on
the same plot.
The second chunk of codes creates a vector
of weights to use for the mixture and creates
an object called pdfmix for the mixture pdf
via a user defined function and then superimposes
a plot of the mixture pdf onto the plot of
the individual subpopulation pdfs.
Under a continuous mixture, we are dealing
with a mixture with an infinite number of
subpopulations, which means the k goes to
infinity.
Here, the subpopulations are not distinguished
by a discrete mixing parameter but by a continuous
variable, theta, where theta plays the role
of the alphas in the finite mixture.
Now, consider a random variable X with a distribution
depending on a parameter theta, where theta
itself is a continuous variable.
We assume the random variable theta has a
pdf f of theta. In the Bayesian context, this
is known as the prior distribution of theta,
which is prior information or experts opinion
used in the analysis.
The cdf of X is equal to the expected value
of the conditional cdf of X given theta. Which
breaks down to the integral of the conditional
cdf of X given theta multiplied by pdf of
theta
Then we obtain the pdf of X by differentiating
the cdf.
Now we show that Gama mixtures of exponential
lead to Pareto distribution.
Suppose we have the conditional pdf of X given
theta follows an exponential distribution
with parameter theta. Also, suppose theta
follows a Gamma distribution with parameters
alpha and Beta,
Then, the pdf of X is given by the integral
of the conditional pdf of X given theta multiplied
by the pdf of theta.
With some algebra, the results break down
to a Pareto distribution with parameters alpha
and theta=1/beta.
Using the laws of iterated expectations, the
Expected value of X is equal to the expected
value of the conditional Expected value of
X given theta.
Then we can easily extend this to the kth
moment of the mixture distribution. Which
implies, the Expected value of X to the power
k is equal to the expected value of the conditional
Expected value of X to the power k given theta
Using the law of total variance, we obtain
the unconditional variance X to be the expectation
of the conditional variance plus the variance
of the conditional expectation.
In splicing, we join together different probability
density functions to form a pdf over the support
of a random variable X.
Let alpha_k be the proportion of data points
that fall under known intervals of support
c_k-1 to c_k.
Then, the pdf of X is given as a piecewise
function of the alphas multiplied by the different
pdfs over the different support intervals.
It has to be noted that the sum of the alphas
is equal to one and the integral of the different
pdfs over each interval is equal to 1.
In this video, we continued with the foundations
for creating new distributions. Specifically,
we discussed an approach which involves combining
distributions to get new distributions.
Under this approach, we talked about mixing,
which represents a useful way of modeling
data drawn from a heterogeneous population.
We also discussed splicing, which means joining
together different probability density functions
to form a pdf over the support of a random
variable.
In this video, we also provided connections
among distributions. For example, we explained
that a Gamma mixture of Exponentials gives
us a Pareto distribution.
Thank you for watching this video.