Hello, welcome back to this video on introduction
to Loss Data Analytics
My name is Nii Okine; I am an assistant professor
at the Maths Department of Appalachian State
University.
In this video, we are going to continue our
discussion on the impacts of coverage modifications
with a focus on policy limits.
Under a limited policy, the insurer is responsible
for covering the actual loss X up to the limit
of its coverage. This fixed limit of coverage
is called the policy limit and often denoted
by u. If the loss exceeds the policy limit,
the difference X?u has to be paid by the policyholder.
While a higher policy limit means a higher
payout to the insured, it is usually associated
with a higher premium.
Let Y denote the amount of paid claim by the
insurer. The variable Y is known as the limited
loss variable and is denoted by X?u and the
wedge means take the minimum of X or u. Therefore,
the limited loss variable is equal to X for
X less than or equal to u and equal u for
X greater than u.
The limited loss random variable Y is a right
censored variable because values above u are
set equal to u.
It can be seen that the distinction between
YL and YP is not needed under the limited
policy as the insurer will always make a payment.
Even when the distribution of X is continuous,
the distribution of Y is a hybrid combination
of discrete and continuous components.
The discrete part of the distribution is concentrated
at Y=u, when X>u, while the continuous part
is spread over the interval Y<u , when X?u.
Also, for the discrete part, the probability
that the loss exceeds the policy limit u is
1? cdf of X at u. And for the continuous part
of the distribution, Y=X.
Hence the pdf of Y is equal to the pdf of
X for y between 0 and u and equal to 1? cdf
of X at u for y=u.
Accordingly, the distribution function of
Y is equal to the cdf of X for y between 0
and u and equal to 1 for values y greater
than or equal to u.
The raw moments of Y can be found directly
using the pdf of X and given as the integral
from 0 to u of X to the power k multiplied
by the pdf of X dx and to account for the
payments of u for X greater than u we add
u to the power k multiplied by 1- cdf of X
at u.
Alternatively, an expression for the moments
can be obtained using the survival function
which is given by the integral from 0 to u
of kx to the power k-1 multiplied by 1- cdf
of X dx.
Therefore when k=1, the expected value of
Y also known as the limited expected value
is equal to the integral from 0 to u of 1-
cdf of X dx.
We now consider a situation where the loss
random variable X follows a Pareto distribution
with parameters theta and alpha.
Recall that for the Pareto distribution, the
survival function of X is given theta/ sum
of x and theta, all to the power alpha and
the mean is given by theta divided by alpha
minus one.
Thus the expected value of Y is equal to the
integral from 0 to u of the survival function
of x that is theta/ sum of x and theta, all
to the power alpha dx.
With some algebra, we obtain the expected
value of Y equals to theta divided by alpha-1
multiplied by 1- theta/ sum of u and theta,
all to the power alpha-1.
Using the definitions of the payment per loss
variable which takes the positive of X?d and
the limited loss variable which takes the
minimum of X and d, it can be easily seen
that the loss random variable X is equal to
the payment per loss random variable and the
limited loss random variable.
This implies, the expected payment without
any coverage modification, E(X), is equal
to the sum of the expected payments with deductible
d and limit d.
We now consider a scenario where the loss
random variable X follows a Pareto distribution
with parameters theta and alpha.
Thus the expected value of X is equal to theta
divided by alpha -1. From the previous slide
we saw the expression for the expected value
of the limited loss variable using a Pareto
distribution.
Then we can find the expected value of the
payment per loss random variable by subtracting
the expected limited loss random variable
from the expected payment without any coverage
modification, E(X). With some algebra, the
expression for the expected value of the payment
per loss random variable is given as shown.
Recall that, the expected payment without
any coverage modification, E(X), is equal
to the sum of the expected payments with deductible
d and limit d.
From our previous video on deductibles, the
loss elimination ration is equal to the expected
value of the loss random variable without
any coverage modification minus the expected
value of the payment per loss variable, all
divided by the Expected value of the loss
random variable without any coverage modification.
Then the loss elimination ratio can be expressed
as the expected value of the limited loss
variable with limit d divided by the Expected
value of the loss random variable without
any coverage modification.
We now consider an actuarial exam question.
We have been given that under a group insurance
policy, an insurer agrees to pay 100% of the
medical bills incurred during the year by
employees of a small company, up to a maximum
total of one million dollars. The total amount
of bills incurred, X, has pdf equal to x multiplied
by (4-x) all divided by 9 for x between 0
and 3 and equal to zero elsewhere.
Note that x is in millions. We are to calculate
the total amount, in millions of dollars,
the insurer would expect to pay under this
policy.
To answer this question, first, we need to
define the limited random variable Y, which
is equal to x for x less than or equal to
1 and equal to 1 for x greater than 1.
Then, the expected value of the limited loss
variable Y is given by the integral from 0
to 1 of x squared multiplied by (4-x) all
divided by 9 dx + 1 multiplied by the integral
from 1 to 3 of x multiplied by 4-x divided
by 9 dx. Solving gives us 0.935.
Now we discuss an example of R code that we
can use to calculate the limited expected
values under a deductible policy.
For this example, we assume the claim severities
follow a lognormal distribution, and we discuss
two functions to calculate expected values
under a deductible policy.
The first chunk of codes assigns the parameters
for the lognormal distribution and simulates
the claims severities based on lognormal distribution.
The second chunk of codes provides the mlnorm
function, that calculates unlimited expected
values of claim severities and the levlnorm
function that calculates the expected values
of the claims retained by the insured under
a deductible policy based on the lognormal
distribution. As you can see these two functions
are user defined.
The third chunk of codes calculates the lognormal
function's expected value and compares it
to the mean of claims from the claims data.
The final chunk of code calculates the expected
value of the claims retained by the insured
using the levlnorm function and compares it
to the amounts retained by the insured from
claims data. Here the pmin function is different
from the min function. The pmin are applied
to two or more numeric vectors with the same
length. pmin returns the parallel minima of
two or more input vectors, where the output
is a vector of the same length as the input
vectors.
In this video, we discussed the limited loss
random variable which is equal to x for x
less than the policy limit u and equal to
the policy limit u for x greater u.
The limited random variable is a right censored
variable because values above u are set equal
to u.
The expected value of limited random variable
is also known as the limited expected value.
We also showed that using the definitions
of the payment per loss variable and the limited
loss variable, it can be easily seen that
the loss random variable X is equal to the
sum of payment per loss random variable and
the limited loss random variable. Which implies,
the expected payment without any coverage
modification, E(X), is equal to the sum of
the expected payments with deductible u and
policy limit. U.
Finally, the limited expected value is equal
to the integral from 0 to u of the survival
function of X dx.
Thank you for watching this video.