Hello, my name is Fei Huang, a senior lecturer
at the UNSW Sydney.
In this video, we will review the maximum
likelihood estimation.
In particular, we review how to define a likelihood
for a sample of observations from a continuous
distribution, define the maximum likelihood
estimator for a random sample of observations
from a continuous distribution, and estimate
parametric distributions based on grouped,
censored, and truncated data.
In previous sections, we have learned various
parametric distributions that are commonly
used in insurance applications. However, to
be useful in applied work, these distributions
must be calibrated based on real data. At
a foundational level, we assume that an analyst
has available a random sample X_1, X_n from
a distribution with distribution function
F_x. We use the vector \theta to denote the
set of parameters for F_x. We use uppercase
roman letter for random variables and lowercase
ones for realizations. With continuous data,
we consider the joint probability density
function. With the independence assumption,
the joint pdf may be written as the product
of pdfs. Thus, we define the likelihood to
be this formular in this slide. Here, note
that we consider this to be a function of
the parameters in \theta, with the data {x_1,
x_2, , x_n} held fixed. The maximum likelihood
estimator is the value of the parameters in
\theta that maximize L(\theta). In this case,
each individual observation is recorded and
its contribution to the likelihood function
is the density at that value. To ease computational
considerations, it is common to consider the
logarithmic likelihood, denoted in the formula
at the bottom of this slide. We can determine
the maximum value of the logarithmic likelihood
by taking derivatives and setting it equal
to zero. We could use statistical routines,
such as the R function optim to do this job.
We could also use the delta method to derive
the asymptotic variance of maximum likelihood
estimators of the model parameters.
In many applications, actuaries and other
analysts wish to estimate model parameters
based on individual data that are not limited.
However, there are also important applications
when only limited, or modified, data are available.
The following section reviews maximum likelihood
estimation for grouped, censored, and truncated
data.
In the previous section, we considered the
maximum likelihood estimation of continuous
models from complete data. Each individual
observation is recorded and its contribution
to the likelihood function is the density
at that value. In this slide we review the
problem of obtaining maximum likelihood estimates
of parameters from grouped data. The observations
are only available in grouped form, and the
contribution of each observation to the likelihood
function is the probability of falling in
a specific group. Let n_j represent the number
of observations in the interval (c_j-1, c_j),
the Grouped data likelihood function is thus
given by the formula in this slide, where
c_0 is the smallest possible observation and
c_k is the largest possible observation.
Another possible distinguishing feature of
a data gathering mechanism is censoring. While
for some events of interest, the complete
data may be available, for others only partial
information is available all that may be known
is that the observation exceeds a specific
value. An example is the limited policy introduced
in Section 3.4.2 of the Loss Data Analytics
open book, which is an example of right censoring.
Any loss greater than or equal to the policy
limit is recorded at the limit. The contribution
of the censored observation to the likelihood
function is the probability of the random
variable exceeding this specific limit. Note
that contributions of both complete and censored
data share the survival function for a complete
point and this survival function is multiplied
by the hazard function, but for a censored
observation it is not. Hence, the likelihood
function for censored data is given by the
formula in this slide, where r is the number
of known loss amounts below the limit u and
m is the number of loss amounts larger than
the limit u.
In this slide, we review the maximum likelihood
estimation of incomplete data due to truncation.
If the values of X are truncated at d, then
it should be noted that we would not have
been aware of the existence of these values
had they not exceeded d. The policy deductible
introduced in Section 3.4.1 is an example
of left truncation. Any loss less than or
equal to the deductible is not recorded. The
contribution to the likelihood function of
an observation x truncated at d will be a
conditional probability and the f_x(x) will
be replaced by fX(x)/S_x(d). The likelihood
function for truncated data is given by the
formula in this slide, where k is the number
of loss amounts larger than the deductible
d.
In this section, you will find 2 exercises.
The first exercise is about finding the maximum
likelihood estimates, while the second exercise
is about calculating confidence intervals
for the parameter estimates we found in the
first exercise. In particular, in Exercise
3.5.1, we extract claim severity data from
the Wisconsin Property Fund. For this exercise
we will undertake maximum likelihood estimation
to fit a Pareto distribution to claim severity
data.
Because we have two parameters in a Pareto
distribution, undertaking maximum likelihood
involves finding the estimates that maximise
the likelihood surface. Visualising the likelihood
surface may help to gain an appreciation of
how maximum likelihood works. After finding
the parameter estimates, we ask you to plot
out a contour plot of the likelihood and mark
the maximum likelihood estimates on the plot.
The pdf function for a Pareto distribution
[dpareto] was created in exercise 3.2.3. It
can be used when finding the negative log-likelihood.
You can also use `optim` to minimise the negative
log-likelihood. R function contour` can be
used to plot the likelihood and R function
`points` can be used to mark the maximum likelihood
estimates on the plot.
In Exercise 3.5.2, you are asked to calculate
95% confidence intervals for the parameter
estimates that we found in Exercise 3.5.1.
The parameters that we have estimated depend
on the data, and since the data can be considered
as a random sample from a larger unknown population,
maximum likelihood estimators are random variables.
A property of maximum likelihood is that the
estimators converge in distribution to a normal
distribution, as n gets larger. If we minimise
the negative log-likelihood, we can use the
Hessian matrix (which is a matrix of the second-order
partial derivatives) to find the variance
of the estimators. Specifically, the standard
errors of the estimators are equal to the
square root of the diagonal elements of the
inverse of the Hessian matrix. In R , we could
use the solve function to find the inverse
of a square matrix, use the diag function
to extract the diagonal of a matrix, use the
`qnorm` function to find quantiles of a normal
distribution.
In summary, in this section, we learned how
to define a likelihood for a sample of observations
from a continuous distribution, define the
maximum likelihood estimator for a random
sample of observations from a continuous distribution,
estimate parametric distributions based on
grouped, censored, and truncated data.