Hello, welcome back to this video on
introduction to Loss Data Analytics
My name is Nii Okine; I am an assistant
professor at the Maths Department of
Appalachian State University.
In this video, I will discuss the
impacts of coverage modifications with a
focus on policyholder deductibles.
We now consider a risk retention framework
where an insurer is obligated to pay
a portion of a loss amount X suffered by an
insured under an insurance contract. We denote Y
to be the insurer s payment.
This section introduces standard
mechanisms that insurers use to reduce or
mitigate their risk, including deductibles,
policy limits, and coinsurance. We
will also introduce reinsurance,
an insurance mechanism for insurance
companies. Further, we will examine
how the distribution of the insurer s
obligations depends on these mechanisms.
In this video, we focus on
impacts of deductibles.
Under an ordinary deductible policy, the insured
(policyholder) agrees to cover a fixed amount
of an insurance claim before the insurer
starts to pay. This fixed expense paid
out of pocket is called the deductible and
often denoted by d. If the loss exceeds d,
then the insurer is responsible for covering
the loss X less the deductible d.
Depending on the agreement, the
deductible may apply to each covered loss
or the total losses during a defined benefit
period (such as a month, year, etc.)
Regarding the benefit paid to the policyholder
Y, we differentiate between two variables:
The payment per loss variable and
the payment per payment variable.
The payment per loss variable is denoted
by YL or (X-d)+, where (X-d)+ means
take the positive part of of the X-d variable.
The payment per loss is equal to zero for values
of X that are less than or equal to d
and equal to X-d for values of X that
are greater than d. Hence it is referred to
as a left-censored and shifted variable.
On the other hand, the payment per payment
variable denoted by YP is defined only when
there is a payment. Specifically, YP equals
X?d on the event X is greater than d.
Here, YP is often referred to as
left truncated and shifted variable
or excess loss variable because the
claims smaller than d are not reported,
and values above d are shifted by d.
Even when the distribution of X is continuous,
the distribution of the payment per loss
variable YL is a hybrid combination of
discrete and continuous components. The discrete
part of the distribution is concentrated at Y=0
when X?d, and the continuous part is
spread over the interval Y>0, when X>d.
For the discrete part, the
probability that no payment is made
is the probability that losses
fall below the deductible;
which is equal to the cdf of X at d.
Also, using the transformation YL=X?d
for the continuous part of the distribution,
the pdf of YL is equal to cdf of X at d
when y=0 and equal to pdf of X at y+d when y>0.
Accordingly, the cdf of YL is equal to cdf of X
at d when y=0 and equal to the cdf
of X at y+d when y>0.
We can see that the payment per payment
variable is the payment per loss
variable conditional on the loss exceeding the
deductible. Alternatively, YP can be expressed
as the loss in excess of the deductible given
that the loss exceeds the deductible. Hence,
the pdf of YP is given by pdf of X at y+d divided
by 1- cdf of X at d for y greater than zero.
Accordingly, the distribution function of YP can
be found directly using the pdf of X and equal to
the cdf of X at y+d - cdf of X at d all divided by
1- cdf of X at d for y greater than zero.
The raw moments of YL can be found directly
using the pdf of X and given as the integral
from d to infinity of X-d to the power
k multiplied by the pdf of X dx.
Similarly, the raw moments of YP
are given by the raw moments of YL
divided by 1- the cdf of X at d.
When k=1, we can use the survival
function to calculate the expected value of YL
and given by the integral from d to infinity
of 1- cdf of X dx. This could be
easily proved if we start with the
initial definition of expected payment per loss
variable and use integration by parts.
Also, when k=1, the expected value of
YP is known as mean excess loss ex(d)
and equal to the expected value of YL
divided by 1- the cdf of X at d.
We now consider an actuarial exam question.
We have been given that losses have the density
function equal to 0.02x for x values
between 0 and 10 or zero otherwise.
Further, the insurance has an ordinary
deductible of 4 per loss. If we define YP
as the claim payment per payment random variable,
we want to calculate the expected value of YP.
To answer this question, first, we need to define
the YP random variable, which is defined only when
there is a payment, i.e., YP equals X?4 on
the event the loss X is greater than 4.
Then, the expected value of YP also known
as mean excess loss can be expressed
as the integral from 4 to 10 of (x-4)
multiplied by 0.02x dx, all divided by 1-
the cdf of X at 4. Solving gives us 3.43
Note that we divide by survival at 4, i.e.,
1- the cdf of X at 4, as this is the probability
where the variable YP is defined.
We have seen that the deductible d imposed
on an insurance policy is the amount of
loss that has to be paid out of pocket
before the insurer makes any payment.
The deductible d imposed on an insurance
policy reduces the insurer s payment and
reduce premiums for the policyholders.
The loss elimination ratio is the percentage
decrease in the expected payment of the
insurer as a result of imposing the deductible.
It is defined as the expected value of the loss
random variable without any coverage modification
minus the expected value of the payment per
loss variable, all divided by the expected
value of the loss random variable without
any coverage modification.
A little less common type of policy
deductible is the franchise deductible.
The franchise deductible will apply to the
policy in the same way as ordinary deductible
except that when the loss
exceeds the deductible d,
the full loss is covered by the insurer.
The payment per loss variable YL takes the
value of zero for values of X that are less than
or equal to d and the value of X for values of
X that are greater than d.
On the other hand,
the payment per payment variable YP is equal X
on the event X is greater than d.
In this video, under an ordinary deductible
policy we differentiate between two variables:
The payment per payment variable YP and
the payment per loss variable YL.
These two variables are based on what
information is available to the insurer.
The payment per payment variable YP is often
referred to as left truncated and shifted
variable or excess loss variable because
the claims smaller than d are not reported,
and values above d are shifted by d.
The expected value of YP is known as mean
excess loss e(d).
The payment per loss variable
YL is equal to zero for values of X that are less
than or equal to d and equal to X-d for values of
X that are greater than d. Hence it is referred
to as a left-censored and shifted variable.
The expected value of YL
can be written as the mean
excess loss e(d) multiplied by survival at d.
Also, we can use the survival function to
calculate the expected value of YL
which is given by the integral from d
to infinity of the survival of X dx.
Thank you for watching this video.