Hello, my name is Fei Huang, a senior
lecturer at the UNSW Sydney.
In this video we will review Section
3.1 Basic Distributional Quantities.
In particular, we learn how to define
some basic distributional quantities,
including moments, percentiles,
and generating functions.
We first define raw moments. Let X be a continuous
random variable with probability density function
f_x(x) and distribution function F_x(x). The
k-th raw moment of X, denoted by \mu_k , is the
expected value of the k-th power of X, provided
it exists. We can see that the formula for the
k-th raw moment is presented at the bottom of the
slide. A special case is the first raw moment,
which is the mean of X, denoted by \mu.
Next, we define the central moment of X, denoted
by \mu_k, which is the expected value of the k-th
power of the deviation of X from its mean \mu. The
formula for \mu_k is given on this slide. We can
see that compared with the raw moment formula, the
central moment focuses on the deviation of X from
its mean \mu, while the raw moment focuses on X.
A special case is the second central moment,
which is the variance of X denoted by \sigma^2.
The square root of the variance is
the standard deviation \sigma.
Now we consider two additional special cases
based on the third and the fourth central moments,
skewness and kurtosis. Skewness is a measure
of symmetry of the probability distribution,
defined as the ratio of the third central
moment to the cube of the standard deviation. A
positive coefficient of skewness indicates that
the distribution is skewed to the right. We also
call it positively skewed. Kurtosis is a measure
of the tailedness of the probability distribution,
defined as the ratio of the fourth central moment
to the fourth power of the standard deviation.
The normal distribution has a coefficient of
kurtosis of 3. Distributions with a coefficient
of kurtosis greater than 3 have heavier
tails than the normal, whereas distribution
with a coefficient of kurtosis less than
3 have lighter tails and are flatter.
In Section 3.1.2 we discuss the concept
of quantiles. When the distribution of
X is continuous, for a given fraction p,
the corresponding quantile is the solution of the
equation in this formula. For example, when p=0.5,
\pi_0.5 is the middle point of the distribution,
called the median. You may come across another
similar concept, called the percentile.
A percentile is a type of quantile;
a 100p percentile is the number such that
100p percent of the data is below it.
In this slide we can see the relationship
between mean and median under different skewness.
For symmetrical distribution, the mean and
median are the same. However, for a positively
skewed (or right-skewed) distribution, the mean
is bigger than the median. And for a negatively
skewed (or left-skewed) distribution, the
mean is smaller than the median.
In Section 3.1.3, we discuss the moment
generating function (mgf), denoted by M_X(t).
Moment generating function uniquely characterizes
the distribution of X. As we can see from the
formula given in this slide, the mgf is defined as
the expectation of e^, for all t for which the
expected value exists. We can see that the k-th
derivative at zero is equal to the k-th raw moment
of X, as shown by the formula at the bottom.
A related concept to moment generating function
is the probability generating function. The
probability generating function can be computed
using the moment generating function of log z. The
probability mass function of X can be recovered by
taking derivatives of the probability generating
function for discrete random variables.
In Exercise 3.1.1, you will
be given a dataset called
Anscombe s quartet. In this exercise, you
will consider 4 variables, y1, y2, y3 and y4.
And you will be able to summarise the data
through summary, mean, var, and sd R functions.
You will also practice the calculation
of the coefficient of skewness.
Exercise 3.1.2 uses the data of the Wisconsin
Property Fund. It includes claim values y as
well as the claim year Year. For this exercise you
will work with the natural logarithm of the claim
values which are in the lny variable. We have
filtered the data to exclude zero claims. This
exercise is to help you understand the shape of a
distribution, and changes in the shape as another
variable changes through the boxplot function.
You will be able to use the quantile function to
evaluate different "percentile" values.
Here we can see an illustration of boxplot.
Boxplots have been a very popular statistical
graphic, especially for exploratory data analysis
when you re trying to understand the data.
As we can see in this plot, it shows the minimum,
maximum, median, as well as 25th and
75th percentiles in a compact way.
In Exercise 3.1.3, you will be able to
apply the moment generating function
using R for a gamma distribution. This exercise
references some low-level functions like eval
and parse. It also mentions how environments
work. These topics are helpful for developing
an advanced understanding of R. The parse function
converts a character vector to an expression.
Then, you can use the eval function to
evaluate the expression. You can also use
the D function to compute derivatives. For
more information about these R functions,
please check the corresponding R help
manual using the help() function.
In this section, we learned how to define
some basic distributional quantities,
including moments, percentiles, and
generating functions.