Welcome back to the tutorial on collective
risk model. My name is Peng Shi, a professor
in the Risk and Insurance department at the
University of Wisconsin-Madison.
In this video, I am going to discuss several
numerical strategies for computing the aggregate
loss distribution from the collective risk
model.
Recall that the aggregate loss follows a compound
distribution, and in general its distribution
cannot be derived analytically. We will introduce
three numerical methods: the direct calculation,
the recursive method, and the Monte Carlo
simulation. We illustrate these methods using
R package actuar. The direct calculation involves
the convolution of a distribution, the recursive
method avoids convolution and saves some computational
time, and the Monte Carlo simulation approximates
the distribution using the empirical cdf.
The first method is the direct calculation.
As we see, the calculation involves the n
-fold convolution of the severity distribution.
For computing the distribution in Rusing the
convolution, the distributions of frequency
N and severity X
must be defined on non-negative integers and
have a finite support. Thus, one has to discretize
the severity distribution so that its support
is discrete and finite.
Consider an example. The frequency and severity
distributions are given in the table. We observe
that the severity outcomes are multiples of
50, so we first discretize its distribution
so that it has support of .
We use function aggregateDist in the actuar
package to compute the distribution of the
aggregate loss. First one defines the frequency
probability pnand the severity probability
fx. In aggregateDist function, one specifies
method = convolution. Arguments model.freq
and model.sev are supplied by pn and fx respectively.
x.scale=50 indicates possible outcomes of
the claim amount are multiples of 50.
One names the distribution Fs. plot(Fs) shows
the cdf of the aggregate loss. The jumps in
the cdf indicates the discreteness of the
aggregate loss, which is anticipated because
both frequency and severity distributions
are discrete.
The second approach for computing aggregate
loss distribution is the recursive method.
To use recursive method, the probability function
for the frequency component has to satisfy
relation pn=(a+b/n)pn−1
for some constants a and b. Similar to direct
calculation, the severity distribution must
have a finite support on non-negative integers.
For continuous distributions, one needs to
discretize them before using the recursive
method. Finally, the method can be extended
to the more general case where the recursive
relationship in frequency distribution starts
from n=2 instead of n=1.
Consider an example where the number of claims
is Poisson with mean of 5. The distribution
of individual claim amount is the same as
the previous example.
In R, one specifies method = recursive in
the aggregateDist function to indicate using
recursive method. model.freq must be from
either (a,b,0) or (a,b,1) class, i.e. to satisfy
the recursive relationship.
The aggregate loss distribution can also be
approximated using the empirical cdf. We could
use Monte Carlo simulation to generate a random
sample of the aggregate loss. To do this,
one first generates the number of claims.
Given claim count, one generates the amount
of loss for each claim. Calculating the total
losses from all claims, we obtain one realization
of aggregate loss. A random sample is obtained
by repeating the process for a large number
of times.
In this example, we define the frequency distribution
to be a Poisson with lambda 3, and the severity
distribution to be a gamma with shape parameter
100, and scale parameter 5. In function aggregateDist,
one indicates method = simulation. The plot
of the empirical cdf is based on 2500 realizations
of the aggregate loss.
To summarize, in this section, we have learned
how to compute the aggregate loss distribution
using convolution, recursive method, and Monte
Carlo simulation. We have also demonstrated
these numerical strategies in R. Thanks for
watching.