Welcome to the tutorial on aggregate loss
models. My name is Peng Shi, a professor in
the Risk and Insurance department at
the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
In this video, I am going to give an
introduction to aggregate loss models.
A primary focus of insurers is to estimate
the cost of insured events under the insurance
contracts. Intuitively, we know that the total
losses to an insurer are affected by both the
frequency and the severity of the insured event.
This chapter will discuss probability models
for aggregate losses that use frequency
and severity as building blocks.
In previous chapters, we have discussed reasons
why frequency and severity are often studied
separately, and we have learned basic probability
models for frequency and severity. Let’s review
some important terminologies that we
continue to use in this section.
Loss, also known as ground-up loss, refers to the
amount of financial losses of the insured. Claim
represents the amount of losses covered by the
insurer. The distinction between loss and claim
is due to the contractual provisions
such as deductible and policy limit.
Frequency measures how often an insured
event occurs during the policy year.
Severity describes the amount or
size of losses for an insured event.
Aggregate losses or aggregate claims denote
the total amount of payment by the insurer
for a single policy or an insurance
portfolio in a policy year.
The goal of this section is to build a
probability model for the total payments
by an insurance system in a fixed time period. One
thinks of an insurance system as a broad concept,
it could be a single insurance contract or a
portfolio of insurance policies that are from
either a line of business or an insurer’s entire
book of business. We will show that frequency
and severity are the building blocks that one
uses to construct the aggregate loss model.
We introduce two approaches for aggregating
losses on a defined set of insurance contracts
over a fixed time period, the individual
risk model and the collective risk model.
In the individual risk model, one records
the losses for each individual claim
and then add them up to obtain the total amount of
losses. In contrast, in the collective risk model,
one records the losses at policy level, then the
total losses are calculated as the sum of losses
from all individual policies. One should
note that the two methods are equivalent
and lead to the same amount of total
losses for the insurance portfolio.
To illustrate the concepts, let’s consider a toy
example. Assume an insurance portfolio consists
of four contracts. The table summarizes
their claim histories during the policy year.
Policy #1 had no claims, and Policy #2,
Policy #3, and Policy #4 had one, two, and
three claims respectively. The loss amount
for each claim is 10 dollars. To obtain the
total losses for the portfolio, the individual
risk model examines losses for each policy,
i.e. 0, 10, 20, 30 dollars for the four policies.
In contrast, the collective risk model records
6 claims and a 10-dollar loss for each claim. Both
methods calculate a total losses of 60 dollars.
Aggregate loss models can be useful
in various actuarial applications.
For instance, in ratemaking, an aggregate loss
model can be used to model the total losses
for a single policyholder in the contract
year, and insurers are interested in the
expected amount of losses for pricing purposes.
In capital management and risk financing,
it is sensible to consider an aggregate loss model
for an insurance portfolio. In these applications,
insurers are more concerned with the large losses
on the tail of the aggregate loss distribution.
To summarize, in this section, we have learned
how to record aggregate losses for an insurance
system. We introduced the basic concepts of two
equivalent methods, the individual risk model
and the collective risk model. We also discussed a
range of actuarial applications of aggregate loss
models, including ratemaking, capital management,
and risk financing. Thanks for watching.