Welcome back to the tutorial on aggregate
loss models. My name is Peng Shi,
a professor in the Risk and Insurance department
at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. In this
video, I am going to introduce a particular
compound distribution known as Tweedie.
The Tweedie distribution is the basis for what
is known by insurers as the pure premium model.
It provides an alternative framework for pricing
insurance coverage, and as we will show, it does
not require decomposing the aggregate losses
into the frequency and severity components.
The Tweedie distribution is defined as
a Poisson sum of gamma random variables.
Specifically, consider the collective
risk model, S is equal to the sum of Y1
to YN. Recall that we interpret S as the total
losses for an insurance system in one period,
where N indicates the number of claims, and
Y indicates the size of the individual claim.
When N is a Poisson with mean λ, and Y is a Gamma
with shape parameter α and scale parameter θ,
the distribution of S is known as Tweedie.
One can further extend the model to incorporate
exposure, and express the aggregate
losses on a per-exposure basis.
Let ω be the exposure. By dividing by ω,
we interpret S as the aggregate losses
per unit of exposure. In this case, the frequency
becomes a Poisson with mean ω times λ, where we
assume that the number of claims is proportional
to the exposure. The severity remains the same.
The distribution function can be derived
using the law of total probabilities,
thinking of frequency N as a partition
of sample space. In the calculation,
we use the fact that given frequency N,
aggregate loss S is a gamma distribution.
It should be noted that the Tweedie
distribution has a probability mass at zero,
that is, S=0 when N=0, and an
otherwise continuous component.
If we reparameterize the Tweedie
distribution using μ, p, and ϕ,
we could show that for p between 1 and 2,
the Tweedie distribution belongs to the
exponential family. In particular, the mean of
the distribution is equal to μ, and the variance
of the distribution is a power function
of the mean. This result suggests that
techniques for fitting generalized
linear models are ready to apply.
Let’s use a toy example to
demonstrate model fitting.
Consider annual medical expenses from a randomly
selected 5,000 individuals. The histogram
shows that a significant portion of subjects
did not incur any expenses over the year.
For those with positive expenses, the
distribution is right skewed and heavy tailed.
To fit a Tweedie distribution in R, we use the
glm function in the package statmod. In the
estimation, we need to assume power parameter p
is known. For instance, we set it to be 1.2.
In the glm function, var.power specifies
the power of the variance function,
and link.power specifies the link function
for the mean, with zero indicating a log link.
We could further extract the estimates for mean μ
and dispersion ϕ using the summary() function.
We can examine the goodness-of-fit of
the model using qq plot. The package
tweedie provides functions that allow
us to calculate probability, quantiles,
and also simulate random realizations
for the Tweedie distribution.
To generate the qq plot, we use function qtweedie
to obtain the theoretical quantiles of the fitted
Tweedie distribution, and function quantile to
obtain the empirical quantiles of the data.
The qq plot shows a linear relation between
the theoretical quantiles of the fitted
Tweedie distribution and empirical
quantiles of the data. Hence the
Tweedie distribution fits the data pretty well.
To summarize, in this section, we have learned
how to construct the Tweedie distribution from
a collective risk model, establish the Tweedie
distribution as a member of the exponential family
of distributions, and fit Tweedie distribution as
a generalized linear model. Thanks for watching.