Scripts:
Slide 0: Welcome back to the tutorial
on aggregate loss models. My name is Peng Shi, a
professor in actuarial science at the University
of Wisconsin-Madison. In this video, I introduce
the collective risk model that examines the
aggregate losses from an insurance entity using
frequency and severity as building blocks.
Slide 1: In the introduction, we have learned that
conceptually a collective risk model examines the
losses at claim level, and calculates the
total losses from all individual claims.
Slide 2: Consider an insurance entity, be
it a single policyholder or a portfolio of
policyholders. For a fixed period of time, let N
be the number of claims of the insurance entity,
and (X1,…,XN) be the corresponding amount of
losses of individual claims. Then the aggregate
loss S is defined as the sum of X1,…,XN. We
emphasize that in the collective risk model, N
is a random number, which is in contrast
to the individual risk model.
There are several key assumptions
in the collective risk model:
first, conditional on N=n
, X1,…,Xn are i.i.d. random variables;
second, the number of claims and the individual
claim amount are independent with each other,
that is, the distribution of N does not depend
on X1,…,XN, nor does the common distribution of
X1,…,XN on N
.
In this model, we refer to N
as claim frequency, and X
as claim severity. We note that frequency
and severity are the two building blocks
in a collective risk model.
Slide 3: The aggregate loss S
is said to follow a compound distribution.
Its distribution function and density function
can be evaluated using the law of total
probabilities. As we see, the computation
involves the n-fold convolution of X
, which makes it a challenging task.
We will discuss computing the distribution
of aggregate loss in a separate video.
Slide 4: Despite the challenge in computing
distributional functions, the moments of S
are ready to calculate. Using the law of iterated
expectations, one could show that the mean of S
is equal to the product of expected
frequency and expected severity of claims.
In addition, the variance of S is
obtained using the law of total variation.
Both results rely on the independence
assumption between N and X
.
Slide 5:
Now let’s examine the model building process. The
assumptions suggest that a collective risk model
can be built in three steps: First, one
develops a frequency model for outcome N
; Second, one develops a severity model
for outcome X; The last step combines the
frequency and severity components
to obtain the distribution of S
.
Slide 6:
As you recall, Chapter two and Chapter three
discussed fitting frequency and severity models
respectively. We use the Wisconsin property
fund data as an example to reinforce the ideas.
We take a subsample of observations in year 2010.
In this example, we use a collective risk model
to describe the total losses for an individual
policyholder in a year. The data provides us a
random sample of 1,110 policyholders.
Slide 7: The frequency component is the
number of claims for a policyholder. Variable
N is created to summarize the random sample
of claim frequency. The contingency table shows
the number of policyholders for each value
of claim count. If we specify
a parametric distribution,
such as Poisson or negative binomial, for N
, we could use the techniques introduced in
Chapter 2 to fit the frequency model.
Slide 8:
For the severity component, instead
of using individual claim amount,
we examine the average amount of
claims for individual policyholders.
Variable Xbar is created to summarize the
random sample of average claim severity.
Note that Xbar is only defined for policyholders
with at least one claims, i.e. N>0
. The table shows the descriptive
statistics of average claim amount.
If we specify a parametric distribution
for Xbar, for instance, gamma or Pareto,
we could use the techniques introduced in
Chapter 3 to fit the severity model.
Slide 9: To summarize, in this section, we have
learned how to build a collective risk model
for a portfolio of insurance contracts, calculate
mean and variance of the aggregate loss,
and fit frequency and severity components in
a collective risk model. Thanks for watching.