Welcome to the tutorial on aggregate loss
models. My name is Peng Shi, a professor in
the Risk and Insurance department at
the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
In this video, I discuss the effect of coverage
modifications on the aggregate loss.
Several contractual provisions
of an insurance contract
could affect the aggregate loss of the
insurer. This section focuses on deductible.
We discuss two types of deductibles, the aggregate
deductible and the per-occurrence deductible.
The aggregate deductible applies to the
aggregate losses of the insurer. Let S
be the aggregate loss which can be
from either an individual risk model
or a collective risk model. With an
aggregate deductible d, the insurer
is liable for the amount of losses in excess
of the deductible, that is, (S−d)+.
Insurance on aggregate losses, subject to a
deductible, is called stop-loss insurance.
This agreement is often used
between an insurer and a reinsurer,
where the insurer puts a cap d on the
losses from a portfolio of policies.
The expected cost of this insurance
is called the net stop-loss premium.
It can be calculated as difference
between the expected aggregate
loss and the expected losses below deductible.
The calculation requires the knowledge of the
distribution of the aggregate loss, which
we have discussed in previous sections.
The per-occurrence deductible
applies to each loss event.
Therefore, it makes sense to think of
aggregate loss using the collective risk model.
We will see that the deductible affects both claim
frequency and claim severity in this context.
When there is a per-occurrence deductible,
the insurer is only liable for the claims with
ground-up loss greater than the deductible.
In fact, small claims might not even
be reported to the insurer. Let N
be the number of loss events and NP be the
number of payments. One could also interpret
NP as the number of reported claims. We could
represent NP as a compound frequency distribution.
The indicator I is created to count the number
of reported loss events. The probability of
reporting is calculated as the probability
of ground-up loss exceeding deductible.
The relation between the distribution of N
and NP can be established using probability
generating functions. This relation will
allow us to derive the distribution of
NP for a given distribution of N.
For instance, if the number of loss
events N is Poisson with mean λ,
using the probability generating function,
we can show that the number of reported claims
NP is also Poisson with mean vλ, where v
is the probability that the claim amount
is great than deductible. Similar results
can be obtained for other frequency
distributions introduced in Chapter 2.
The per-occurrence deductible affects not only
the number of claims, but also the amount of
each claim. For a given claim, let X be the
ground-up loss and XP be the amount of payments.
Then XP can be calculated as difference
of the ground-up loss and the deductible.
We emphasize that XP is defined only when X>d.
This definition also allows us to establish the
relation between the distributions of XP and X.
Now we have discussed how a per-occurrence
deductible affects claim frequency and claim
severity. Combining the two components,
we can express the insurer’s loss using
a collective risk model, where NP
is the number of reported claims, and XP is the
amount of payments for individual claims.
To summarize, in this section, we
have learned how to price stop-loss
insurance, and examine the effect
of per-occurrence deductible on
frequency and severity components in the
collective risk model. Thanks for watching.