Welcome back to the tutorial on aggregate loss
models. My name is Peng Shi, a professor in
actuarial science at the University
of Wisconsin-Madison. In this video,
I introduce the individual risk model and discuss
its application in short-term insurance.
In the introduction, we have learned that
conceptually an individual risk model examines
the losses at policy level, and calculates the
total losses from all individual policies.
In this section, we formally represent
the model using random variables. Here S
denotes the total losses of a portfolio of n
contracts, and Xi, for i=1,…,n, is the loss
for the ith contract. To emphasize, note that
the number of contracts is fixed and known.
In this model, we typically assume losses from
different contracts are independent with each
other, but not necessarily identically
distributed. This could be due to the
different exposures across the contracts.
Taking homeowner insurance as an example,
one could think that the loss distribution
depends on the value of the property.
One also notes the distribution of Xi
is often featured with a probability mass
at zero, that is, for a given policyholder,
there is a chance that he or she won’t have
any claims during the policy year. We could
easily relate to personal lines of business
such as automobile or homeowner insurance.
Let’s examine some applications
of the individual risk model.
The model was originally developed for life
insurance portfolio. Consider term-life
insurance that pays a fixed amount of insurance
to the beneficiary upon the death of the insured.
For the ith individual in the portfolio, let
qi be the probability of death within a year,
and bi be the payable amount from the insurer
upon death. Then the loss for the ith contract
is described by random variable Xi which
has a probability mass at zero and bi.
In property casualty insurance, it is
more complicated. For a single contract,
one can still think that the policyholder incurs
loss events within a year with probability qi.
However, given occurrence, the amount of loss
is not fixed, instead, it is a random quantity.
In this case, the loss for the ith contract
in the portfolio, denoted by Xi, can be
represented using a two-part framework, where I
indicates the occurrence of loss events, and B
is the amount of losses given occurrence.
Both I and B are random variables,
and B reduces to a fixed amount in
the above life insurance example.
Consider the Wisconsin Property Fund
data that we introduced in Chapter one.
We use data in year 2010 to
illustrate the two-part model.
Variable I is defined as an indicator, with 1
indicating occurrence of claims, and 0 otherwise.
Variable B corresponds to the amount of
losses for the subset of policyholders
with at least one claims. If we take a look at
the length of the two variables, we note that
I is defined for all policyholders, but B is
only defined for a subset of policyholders.
One could also examine the empirical distribution
of variables I and B. As an illustration,
table is used to create the frequency
table for claim frequency. We observe
that the probability of having loss events for
a randomly selected policyholder is about 36%.
summary is used to calculate the
descriptive statistics for claim severity.
We observe that the amount of losses is skewed
and heavy tailed. The above analysis assumes
that the distributions of claim frequency and
severity are i.i.d. across all policyholders.
Last, we discuss computing the distribution for
the aggregate loss. Recall that the aggregates
loss S is defined as the sum of n random
variables. In general, its cdf is difficult to
evaluate due to the multivariate integration
involved in the computation. When Xi are i.i.d.,
it is known as the n-fold convolution of the cdf
of X. We present a couple of examples in R.
In R, function convpow from the distr package
calculates the distribution of the sum of
independent random variables using discrete
Fourier transformation. In the first example,
we determine the distribution of the sum of an
exponential variable and a log-normal variable.
In function convpow, one specifies the sum in the
first argument and 1-fold in the second argument.
Function d returns the
density of the distribution.
The plot visualizes the density of
the sum of the two variables.
In the second example, we examine the 10-fold
convolution of an exponential distribution.
In function convpow, one specifies the exponential
distribution in the first argument and 10-fold
convolution in the second argument. The
plot shows the resulting gamma density.
To summarize, in this section, we have learned
how to build an individual risk model for a
portfolio of insurance contracts, apply individual
risk model in life and nonlife insurance, and
compute the distribution of aggregate losses from
an individual risk model. Thanks for watching.